<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Repentance and prayer or, the two fundamental pillars of the nation. Being the substance of four sermons preached at St. Peters Poor, London. By that famous and reverend divine Ralph Brownrigge, formerly vice-chancelour of Cambridge, and lately Lord Bishop of Exeter.</title>
            <author>Brownrig, Ralph, 1592-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77703</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229484</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899222</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899222</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152582</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77703)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152582)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2306:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Repentance and prayer or, the two fundamental pillars of the nation. Being the substance of four sermons preached at St. Peters Poor, London. By that famous and reverend divine Ralph Brownrigge, formerly vice-chancelour of Cambridge, and lately Lord Bishop of Exeter.</title>
                  <author>Brownrig, Ralph, 1592-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 120, 129-154, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Riland, and are to be sold at the Hand and Bible in Ducklane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text appears to be continuous despite pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152582:1"/>
            <p>REPENTANCE AND PRAYER: OR, The two Fundamental Pillars of the NATION. BEING The ſubſtance of Four Sermons preached at St. <hi>Peters Poor, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By that Famous and Reverend Divine <hi>RALPH BROWNRIGGE,</hi> Formerly Vice-Chancelour of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and lately Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 14.13.</hi>
               </bibl>—Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, from henceforth, yea ſaith the ſpirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Riland,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Ducklane.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152582:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152582:2"/>
            <head>To the READER:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing unwilling the Nation ſhould be deprived of ſo great a benefit as the works of ſo eminently learned and pious a Divine, as this our reverend Author: I could not but (in charity to thee, and in duty to our Authors ſacred memory)
<pb facs="tcp:152582:3"/>offer to publick view theſe Four enſuing Sermons: being prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at St. <hi>Peters Poore</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, when that famous Pillar of the Church, Dr. <hi>Holſworth</hi> was Preacher there. As for the Subject matter of them, it's principally concerning the Duties of <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> the two Fundamental Doctrines, which every indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Chriſtian, and the whole Nation in general ought to put in practice; which duties as they were then Seaſonably preached, ſo I hope they will be now as opportunely publiſhed;
<pb facs="tcp:152582:3"/>this being an Age, wherein there is ſo much want of both. I ſhall not need to expatiate my ſelf, in giving thee a character of our worthy Author, be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo generally known: I queſtion not but the benefit which thou ſhalt reap by reading them, will anſwer the fervent deſires of him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord <hi>J. K.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:152582:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Texts of the four Sermons.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOEL 2.14.</hi>
               </bibl> WHo knoweth if he will return and repent and leave a bleſſing behind him, even a meat-offering and a drink-offering unto the Lord our God.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM, 78.</hi> verſ. <hi>34, 35, 36, 37.</hi>
               </bibl> When he ſlew them, then they ſought him and turned them early, and enquired aſter God, and they remembred that God was their ſtrength, and that the high God was their Redeemer; nevertheleſs they did but flatter him with their mouth, and diſſembled with him in their tongue, for their heart was not whole with him, neither conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued they ſtedfaſt in his covenant.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LUKE 22.</hi> verſe <hi>31, 32.</hi>
               </bibl> And the Lord ſaid, Simon, Simon, behold, Satan hath deſired to have you, that he may ſift you as wheat: But I have p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thee, that thy faith fail not; and when thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy Brethren.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LUKE 11.13.</hi>
               </bibl> If ye then, being evil; know how to give good gifts unto your Children; how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the holy Spirit to them that ask him?</q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152582:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Joel. <hi>2.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">In Jejunio Publico.</note> Who knoweth if he will return and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and leave a bleſſing behind him, even a meat-offering and a drink-offering unto the Lord our God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His propheſy of <hi>Joel.</hi> 14. It was directed to the Kingdome of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> in the reigne of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> after the great o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-throw which God brought upon the other ten Tribes, by the King of <hi>Aſyria,</hi> and in it the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152582:5"/>foretells the Captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> threatens a great Judgement and diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon the whole Land.</p>
            <p>And this Judgement it is deſcribed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the repreſentation of an army, and that army of Locuſts, either thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating a ſucceſſion of two ſorts of judgements; Firſt of Famine, by a dreadfull ſwarm of noiſome Locuſts, that ſhould conſume the fruit of the earth. the Second is of war, by the power of the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> that ſhould waſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and carry them away Captive to <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two, the breakings of the ſtaffe of bread, or ſending amongſt them the Sword of the enemy which are Gods two puiſſant armies againſt a ſinfull Nation: or otherwiſe, the Army of Locuſts, betoken but one Judgement, either that of Locuſts, noyſome vermine ſhall come upon their Land like a mighty Army, he deſtroyed <hi>Egypt</hi> with ſuch an Army, and verſe. 25. God himſelfe calls them his great Army or elſe it ſignifies the Army of the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> and they ſhall come upon the Land like a ſwarme of Locuſts to waſt and deſtroy.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152582:5"/>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> are compared to Bees and Flies, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.18. God ſhall hiſſe for them, and they ſhall come flying, and light upon the Land of <hi>Judah,</hi> take them either way, the one is a fit reſemblance and tipe of the other, the Locuſt they are Gods Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, they ſhall come in battle aray and make ſpoile of the Land; or otherwiſe, the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> they are as a ſwarme of Locuſts, their enemies ſhall breake in upon them like Caterpillers and Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts, and ſhall waſte and conſume, as thoſe creatures do without any reſiſtance. This judgement being denounced againſt them, the Prophet calls the <hi>Jews</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>entance, that being the onely poſſible means to divert this judgement.</p>
            <p>Fleſh and blood indeed, when we heat of Armies of enemies, caſt about for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her waies to defend them; this ſeeking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o God by repentance, and caſting our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elves upon his help, they have no liſt to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; when the <hi>Aſſirians</hi> aſſaulted <hi>Judah,</hi> God offered King <hi>Ahaz,</hi> this help, no, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not trouble God, he would not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>empt the Lord forſooth, he was ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152582:6"/>as not to be beholden to God for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deliverance; any other way would pleaſe him better, as <hi>Dominicus Soto</hi> tells us, of a ridiculous and ſuperſtitious practice i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Spain,</hi> to drive away Locuſts, when thoſe ſwarms, anoyed the Country, the country people would enter an action againſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in their Courts; and Proctors and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates, were aſſigned to plead for them and then the Judge, he ſentenced them and did excommunicate and accurſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them.</p>
            <p>Sure all others meanes without this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> repentance are of no uſe, meere charm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and mock-helps; neither Caterpille<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> Armies of Locuſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſwarmes of enemies, can be driven bac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but by repentance; ſo then the pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the Prophet in this Chapter to call them to repentance, and he pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes repentance ſuitable to their co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition;</p>
            <p>Firſt to the condition of their ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their ſins were generall and nationa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they had all corrupted their wayes.</p>
            <p>Secondly the judgement threate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that was generall, an over-flowing ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152582:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> calls it. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15. Sword goe through the Land: <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.17. An end is comming upon the four corners of the Land. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.2. Now ſure the Plaiſter muſt be as broad as the ſore.</p>
            <p>Firſt. So accordingly he invites to a generall and nationall humiliation, it was to be proclaimed by the ſound of the Trumpet, verſ. 15. not by a knock at a private mans doore, the trumpet was to call together the whole congregation, <hi>Num.</hi> 10.2. And if ye look to the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſe of this 2 <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Joel,</hi> then the judgement comes with a trumpet, it ſounds an allarme, it threatens all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitans of the Land; if God threatens with a trumpet, we muſt call to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with a trumpet; with as lowd and ſhrill a ſound, that the whole nation may be warned; it muſt be <hi>Zephanies</hi> humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iation, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Gather your ſelves together, O Nation not to be deſired,</hi> it muſt be like the faſt of expiation, which was the yearely faſt in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> all muſt numble themſelves, it is a day of atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.28, 29. <hi>For to make an atonement for you before the Lord your God</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152582:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>whatſoever ſoule it ſhall be that ſhall not be afflicted, in the ſame day he ſhall be cut off from among his people; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall, and private humiliation, is not of that prevailing efficacy in generall dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; God tells the <hi>Jewes</hi> that the prayers of two or three, though never ſo righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.14. <hi>As Noah, Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, and Job, ſhould not divert a judgement from a whole Nation,</hi> they might eſcape themſelves; but if the Nation repented not, the whole Land ſhould periſh; there is more muſt go to the removing of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall judgement; we may ſpit out a ſpark, or one mans diligence may quench a ſmall fire, but when a whole Town is on fire, every man muſt bring his Bucket. One mans prayer to remove a National Judgement, is as if we go about to quench a raging fire by ſpri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kling a little water out of a caſting bottle; ſee this practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Jews, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.2. all the houſe of Iſrael lamented before the Lord, and ſee how they expreſſed and teſtified it, <hi>verſe</hi> the 6. they gathered together to <hi>Miſpah,</hi> and draw water, and poured it out before the Lord, and faſted on that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152582:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>day, and ſaid there, we have ſinned againſt the Lord, their eies were as buckets, their heads fountains of tears.</p>
            <p>And is not a fire kindled amongſt us, how many ſmoaking fire-brands are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered through the Land, we may ſay of our preſent ſad condition as our Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Joel.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Hear this you old men and give ear all the Inhabitants of the Land, hath this been in your days, or in the days of your fathers,</hi> who can remember ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions in our kingdome, when did this kingdom ſhake and totter as now it doth; firſt troubles in the North, when thats quenched, the flame breaks out in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſparkes ſcattered amongſt our ſelves, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> propheſies, miſchiefe ſhall come upon miſchiefe, and rumour ſhall come upon rumour, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.26. Thus out hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation ſhould be generall, and as it muſt be generall humiliation, ſo ſecondly it muſt be ſolemne by the help of a faſt not to eat the bread of men.</p>
            <p>Firſt to teſtifie our inward ſorrow, the body muſt be afflicted.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by this ſolemne faſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt our unworthineſſe of the leaſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152582:8"/>of life or refreſhing, not worthy of the portion (of Whelps) of the crumbs that fall from the table.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to expreſſe our earneſtneſſe and importunity of prayer, and calling upon God, that we will lye proſtrate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, take no deniall, not eat bread till he granted our petitions, as <hi>Saul</hi> vowed, not once to eat till he had obteined his victory; as <hi>David</hi> vowed, not to ſleep or ſlumber till he had effected his deſire, now this duty of repentance and humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, it is preſſed upon them by a double motive; the firſt is the denouncing of judgement, and that not barely foretold, but exactly deſcribed in a dreadfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the more to affect them; God muſters up his force and ſets them in battle aray, from the 2. verſe to the 12. the Chariots of God are 20. thouſand, even thouſand of judgements, and the Lord is among them to turn the battle to the gate, ah, this will work feare, and fear is a good ingredient to repentance; thus he urges his people to repentance by the preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of terrours; <hi>Amos</hi> 4.12. <hi>Therefore thus will I doe unto thee O</hi> Iſrael, and becauſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152582:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>I will doe this unto thee prepare to meete thy God O <hi>Iſrael;</hi> thus <hi>Habbakuk</hi> was afflicted with the threatnings of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>ch.</hi> 3.16. when I heard my belly trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, my lips quivered at the voice, rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe entered into my bones, and I trembled in my ſelfe; God lookes for this ſubmiſſion, that we ſhould be ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at his judgements, the Lion hath roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who will not feare, <hi>Amos</hi> the 3.8. moved with feare, thats one motive, and that drives us to repentance.</p>
            <p>But then he adds a ſecond, and thats hope that draws us to repentance; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance it is a compounded thing of feare and hope, it takes motives, both from Law and Goſpell, and yet it workes moſt kindly by Evangelicall means, thats hope of mercy, and that is the motive in my text, <hi>quis novit,</hi> who knows, ſo that the former was an affrightment to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, this in my text is an incouragement to repentance upon hope of mercy, and in it obſerve two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt the matter of their hope.</p>
            <p>Secondly the meaſure of their hope.</p>
            <p>Firſt ſee the matter of their hope and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152582:9"/>in it, there are 4 particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the matter of their hope is, their regaining of Gods favour, he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
            <p>Secondly the recalling of his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he will repent.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the renewing of his mercies, he will leave a bleſſing behinde him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the reeſtabliſhment of his worſhip amongſt them, a meat offering and a drink-offering to the Lord our God, thats the firſt thing, the matter of their hope. The ſecond thing is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their hope, and thats ſomewhat ſtrange, it is very conſiderable, it is <hi>quis novit</hi> who knows. Come we to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their hope.</p>
            <p>The firſt is regaining of Gods favour, that he will return, his turning away ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies his diſpleaſure, that he hath no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in us, but is provoked and offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; his returning to us, it is the renewing of his favour, and of his good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us when he vouchſafes us his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and reſts amongſt us, ſo then for the underſtanding the nature of this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, this return of God will afford us theſe Conſiderations.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152582:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Firſt, it is the main happineſſe of a nation to enjoy Gods preſence, to have him dwell amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is the bitter fruit of ſin that cauſes God to withdraw his preſence and to turn away from us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is the bleſſed fruit of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that recovers Gods preſence, cauſes God to return gratiouſly to us.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay it is the main happineſſe of a Nation to enjoy Gods preſence, to have him dwell amongſt us, this happineſſe by Gods preſence will appear by three great advantages which his preſence, and abode, brings a people.</p>
            <p>The firſt advantage is, Gods preſence and abode with a people it is the holineſs of a Nation, where he dwells and vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes his preſence, that people by vertue of that preſence becomes an holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all Holineſſe comes by participation it is not inbred in us, but derived from him who is holyneſſe it ſelfe, and partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation comes by union with him, a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple neare to him are an holy people, he is the Holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and by that neare relation, they are made an holy people to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152582:10"/>the Lord their God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6. We ſee that this preſence of God makes a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple holy, even by that legal and cerimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all holyneſſe amongſt the <hi>Jewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt the Land of <hi>Iſrael</hi> it was called an holy Land, becauſe God dwelt in it, and vouchſafed his preſence in it; he would not have it polluted or defiled; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file not the Land which ye ſhall inhabit, wherein I dwell, for I the Lord dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Children of <hi>Iſrael, Num.</hi> 35.34.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> it is called an holy City becauſe it was the city of the great King, God dwelt in her palaces, therefore it was accounted a ſacred, and a holy City, the Temple, becauſe his name dwelt there, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.16. I have ſanctified this houſe that my name may be there for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. All other Nations becauſe God was eſtranged from them, were an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane people, every other Land a pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Land; here is one great excellency a Nation gaines by retaining of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, they were more to God then all other Nations in the world, a kingdome of Preiſts and an holy Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152582:10"/>thus we ſee God promiſes to dwell in the midſt of <hi>Sion, Zech.</hi> 2.10. And then he tells them (in the 12th verſe) that he will inherit <hi>Judah</hi> his portion in in the holy Land; for this cauſe the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane were to be put out of the Campe of <hi>Iſrael, Num.</hi> 5.3. <hi>That they defile not their Campe in the midſt whereof God did dwell;</hi> while we retain his preſence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, we are unholy people; but if we cauſe him to depart, we are as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed and a prophane people.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond advantage of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is, that it is the glory of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is the high dignity and renown, and honour of a people that God abides with them, as St <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1. What advantage then hath the Jew, what is this dignity in having God ſo near them? much every way, thus <hi>Moſes</hi> ſets out the dignity of the Jews from the near refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence 'twixt God and them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.18. <hi>God hath avouched thee this day to be his peculiar people, &amp; to make thee high above all Nations which he hath made, in praiſe, and in name, and in honour,</hi> this nearneſs of his preſence he compares (in the 13.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152582:11"/>of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> the 11. verſe) to a girdle, cleaving to his loins; <hi>as a girdle cleaves to the loins of a man, ſo have I cauſed thee to cleave unto me, that they might be unto me for a people, &amp; for a name, and for a praiſe &amp; for a glory:</hi> So likewiſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.4. <hi>Since thou waſt precious in my ſight, thou haſt been honourable, and I have loved thee;</hi> when God reckons up the dignities of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, this is the main, of <hi>Sion,</hi> it ſhall be ſaid that he was born in her; thus <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> reminds the Iſraelites, wherein their dignity conſiſted, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.21. <hi>He is thy praiſe, and he is thy God;</hi> many titles of honour amongſt men, but this is the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honourable title that we have a God near to us, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.7. <hi>What Nation is there ſo great who hath God ſo nigh unto them, as the Lord our God is to us;</hi> while he vouchſafed his preſence to them, how renowned were they, when he withdrew himſelf and caſt them off, then were they a vile people? the hatred and ſcorn and hiſſing of all Nations.</p>
            <p>A third advantage, that Gods preſence brings, it is the ſtrength and ſafety of a Nation, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 46.5. <hi>God is in the midſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152582:11"/>of her, therefore ſhall ſhe not be moved; Balaam</hi> could not faſten a curſe upon <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> while God was amongſt them, and this incouraged the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Canaanites, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.9. <hi>Their defence is departed from them, and the Lord is with us, fear them not, though Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants and Cities walled up to heaven, yet fear them not.</hi> So <hi>Moſes</hi> incourages them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.21. <hi>Thou ſhalt not be affrighted at them, for the Lord thy God is among you, a mighty God and terrible.</hi> And ſo on the contrary, when the people would needs go up to fight againſt the Canaanites, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.42. <hi>Moſes</hi> diſſwaded them, God had then withdrawn himſelf, <hi>Go not up, for the Lord is not among you, Sampſon</hi> wiſt not that God was departed from him, <hi>Moſes</hi> laments when God ſaid he would not go with them; ſo the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, Thou goeſt not forth with our Armies,</hi> his preſence is our <hi>Palladium,</hi> our ſhield and rock, the ſhields of the earth belong unto God; well then if ſuch good comes from Gods preſence amongſt us, it is worth the iniquity, wherein doth this preſence of God conſiſt, how is he ſaid
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152582:12"/>and known to dwell in a Nation? Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath a manifold preſence.</p>
            <p>Firſt his ſubſtantial preſence, ſo he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſent in all places, <hi>he fills heaven an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> earth,</hi> Jer. 23.24. <hi>The heaven of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vens cannot contain him</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon Stand in aw of him,</hi> he is in all places.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he hath a glorious preſenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there where his glory and Majeſty moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appears, that's in the heavens, <hi>I wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dwell in the high and holy place,</hi> Heaven i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Throne.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he hath a powerfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, when he manifeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelf by any remarkable work, thus the Iſraelites que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned his preſence when they were in want, <hi>is the Lord among us yea or no? Jacobs</hi> viſion made him ſay, <hi>God was in this place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, he hath a gratiou, preſence by which he dwells amongſt us, I that gratious, and mercifull, and beneficiall preſence is that we ſpeake of, there where he dwells.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God dwells in a Nation which he chuſes to be his peculiar people, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> people of his Covenant and Worſhip, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152582:12"/>
               <hi>David</hi> ſaid, the Lord hath choſen <hi>Jacob</hi> to be his inheritance, thus <hi>Hoſea</hi> calls the Nation and Countrey of the Jews, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 9.3. the Lords Land, and the world is his by dominion; but by ſpecial pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe and poſſeſſion; ſo the Church is his, that's like the Lords Demeans.</p>
            <p>Secondly the place of Gods delight, that's the reſidence of his preſence, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light fixes a man to his abode, when we are ſuch a people that God takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in us, <hi>Here will I dwell for I have a delight in it,</hi> Pſalm 132.23, 14. <hi>The Lord hath choſen</hi> Sion, <hi>he hath deſired it for his habitation, here will I dwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly there we are to reckon of Gods preſence, where he ſettles his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; that's the uſual place of preſence and abode, where we ſee God gathers to himſelf a Church, is dayly collecting to himſelf a people to know him and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him; there we may conclude that God vouchſafes his preſence, Chriſt is thus deſcribed to walk amongſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven golden Candleſticks, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.13. where it may be ſaid of a people or place as God ſaid of <hi>Corinth, Acts</hi> 18.10. <hi>I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152582:13"/>have much people in this City, many names amongſt you,</hi> there reſolve that God is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; when they grow thinner and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, God is removing.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, There we conclude is a place of preſence and abode, where a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows moſt coſt, a Lord will keep up all his poſſeſſions, ſo doth God the world, but his choiceſt care is for his Manſion-houſe; do we ſee a people inriched with his choiceſt bleſſings, his eyes are over them continually, no favour too dear for them, ſure God dwells amongſt ſuch a people.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, a man is ſaid to dwell where his abode is moſt conſtantly; Sometimes God makes in his progreſs, ſome excurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into other places, as he did to <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve</hi> by <hi>Jonah,</hi> he may be ſometimes as a wayfaring man that lodges for a night, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.18. Some rare tokens of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; but where his Ordinances are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and he fixes them, that's the place of his preſence, we have done with the firſt, his preſence it is the happineſs of a Nation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider, it is the bitter
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152582:13"/>fruit of ſin, that cauſes God to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his preſence, and to turn away from us; this is the malignanant effect of ſin in general, that is parts God and us, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes him to withdraw and turn away from us, his delight is to be in the habitable world, to be amongſt the ſons of men, but ſin and wickedneſs cauſes him to withdraw and eſtrange himſelf from us, thus <hi>Cain</hi> complained, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.14. <hi>I am caſt away from thy face,</hi> So <hi>Saul</hi> upon his diſobedience cried out, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.15. <hi>God is departed from me;</hi> it was the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full condition of all mankind, that by nature we are ſtrangers from God, nay without God in the world, ſo <hi>Paul</hi> tells them at <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> that God ſuffered all Nations to walk in their own wayes, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver owned or regarded them, our ſins ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate twixt God and us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, not only the world of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men reap this fruit by their ſin, but Gods own people find this uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſertion, when they grievonſly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, he turns away from them, this <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhewed them a viſible reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.7. the people there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152582:14"/>had ſinned againſt God, then it is ſaid, <hi>Moſes took the Tabernacle and pitcht it without the Camp, afar off from the Camp;</hi> thereby ſignifying Gods diſpleaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and his departure from them, as appears, the Tabernacle was to be in the midſt of the Hoſt; but he was offended and withdrew himſelf.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, may not onely his viſible Church, but even his darling Saints find this wofull effect, that their ſins brings upon them, that God ſtands aloof off, and withdraws from them; how often doth <hi>David</hi> mourn for this, and pray a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 10.1. <hi>Why ſtandeſt thou afar off O Lord, Why hideſt thou thy ſelf in time of trouble,</hi> Pſalm 38.21. <hi>Forſake me not O Lord, O be not far from me,</hi> upon his ſin of adultery, <hi>O caſt me not away from thy preſence,</hi> this the Saints find often &amp; feel if they turn unto folly, God ſtands afar off, not to hear them, nor to help them, not to own them; <hi>Tertullian</hi> gives a reaſon, the holy ſpirit is a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thing, it will not reſt in a defiled ſoul.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, eſpecially ſome ſins of his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152582:14"/>people are of higher provocation, ſet him off from us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as blood, and oppreſſion and violence, that caſt off <hi>Cain;</hi> ſo God ſayes he would remove <hi>Judah</hi> out of his ſight for the bloodſhed of <hi>Manaſſes, When you make long prayers I will not hear you, your hands are full of blood,</hi> Iſa. 1.15. verſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a ſecure neglect of Gods offers of grace, that turns him from us, when he ſtretches out his hands to us, and we will not come into him, then ſaid God I will get me to my own place. This coſt the Spouſe ſorrow, when Chriſt knockt, and ſhe refuſed to open, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.6. <hi>At laſt I opened to my beloved, but my beloved had withdrawn himſelf, and was gone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, falſeneſs in his covenant, or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>upting of his Religion, that turns him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom us: So what that works, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>My ſoul loathed them and their ſoul alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bhorred me,</hi> it was the caſting off of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſraelites,</hi> Pſal 106.39.40. <hi>They were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led with their own works, and went a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their own inventions,</hi> then he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152582:15"/>abhorred his own inhetitance; it made him forſake the tabernacle in <hi>Shilo,</hi> the tent which he had pitched amongſt them, 78.60.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, incorrigiblneſs in the uſe of the means of reformation, when God ſtrives with them and they reſiſt him, it was the caſe of the old world; his ſpirit ſhould ſtrive no more with them, but he caſt them off. They rebelled againſt him and vexed his holy ſpirit. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.10. <hi>Therefore he was turned to be their enemy and he fought againſt them,</hi> thus God is giving over <hi>Judah</hi> as deſperate, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Why ſhould ye be ſmitten any more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider it is the bleſſed fruit of repentance, that it can recover God preſence, cauſeth him to return graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to us; when I name repentance, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, a reall, cordiall, ſpirituall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that, and that onely can regai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods favour, and return him to us; tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you may the better acquaint your ſelve with this neceſſary and ſoveraign duty not to enter into any large diſcourſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the nature of it, this ſolemn repentance will require of you theſe three actions.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152582:15"/>
            <p>Firſt, humiliation; Secondly, lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deprecation; Thirdly, reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>I will exemple to you out of the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the <hi>Ninivites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, they put themſelves to great hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, the King himſelf roſe from his throne, laid his robes from him, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him with ſackcloth, and ſate in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, nay, man and beaſt were covered with ſackcloth, proſtrating, &amp; debaſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before an angry God; we muſt put our mouthes in the duſt, to be aſhamed, and abaſht, and abhorr our ſelves in duſt and aſhes; thats their humiliation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, their lamentation or depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, they cried mightily unto God; <hi>Jonah</hi> 3. vers 8. The ſpirit of lamentation and ſupplication muſt abound in us; not ordinary perfunctory prayers, but we muſt ſtrive and wreſtle in prayer, as it is ſaid of <hi>Jacob</hi> how he prevailed with God, he had power over the Angell and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, he wept and made ſupplication unto him, <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 12.4.17. This God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to the Prieſts, let the Prieſts the Miniſters of the Lord weep between the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152582:16"/>Porch and the Altar, and ſay ſpare thy people O Lord.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, their reformation, thats a main point in the <hi>Ninivits</hi> repentance, let them every one turn from his evil way, and from the violence that is in their hands, violence that was the ſin of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> it was an oppreſſing people, it was that which mainly prevailed with God, ſee verſe the 10. God ſaw their works that they turned from their evill way, and God repented, he ſaw their humiliation, he heard their lamentation, but yet that which pleaſed him beſt was their refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; thats the fat of the ſacrifice; is this the faſt that I have required or cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, a day for a man to afflict his ſoul, to bow down his head like a bull ruſh, and to ſpread ſackcloth and aſhes under him; is not this the faſt that I have choſen, to looſe the bands of wickedneſs, to let the oppreſſed go free, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.5.6. Such re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is like to prevaile with him, let him be turned away he will draw near to us and vouchſafe us his preſence, ſee two places, Pſal. 38.18. The Lord is nigh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that are of a broken heart, &amp; ſaves
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152582:16"/>all ſuch as be of a contrite ſpirit, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. <hi>I dwell in the high and holy place,</hi> with him alſo that is of a contrite ſpirit, revive the ſpirit of the humble.</p>
            <p>Firſt, repentance ſo pleaſes him that the very thoughts and intendments of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance prevaile with him, thus <hi>David</hi> found it: Pſalm 32.5. <hi>I ſaid I will confeſs my ſins unto the Lord,</hi> and thou forgaveſt the iniquity of my ſin, ſo God promiſed before you ſpeak, I will hear and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer you.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the imperfect acts of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance prevaile with him, if true and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere though not according to the purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the ſanctuary, <hi>David</hi> cries out I have ſinned, preſently God abſolves him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, nay God is ſo propitious to repentance, that even outward repentance (if it be ſerious) hath ſome good ſucceſs with him for the eſcaping of temporal judgements; <hi>Ahab</hi> was a wicked man, his ſorrow was not for ſin, but for fear of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, yet God paſſed by him for that time upon his humiliation; ſo the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> repentance, Pſalm 78. Was an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152582:17"/>repentance, yet upon that he was ſo mercifull that he would not deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>Firſt reaſon, it is the property of a gracious nature to relent upon ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deprecation, not to be implacable and revengefull, it is ſo with men, how much more is God graciouſly inclined, he is ſlow to anger, ready to forgive; two rare properties amongſt men, thoſe that are ſoon angry, if they be ſoon pleaſed, we count them good natures, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary they go too often together, hardly angered and hardly pleaſed; but God is hardly angered, ſoon pleaſed; if thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comes and ſay it repents me, forgive him.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon, eſpecially when the breach is amongſt friends, then love will be ſoon revived, thus it is twixt God and his people, though he be angry, yet he remembers his old loving kindneſſes, as <hi>Iſay.</hi> 16.6. <hi>I will remember the daies of thy youth,</hi> twixt God and his people, there is a league of love, and love it is ſoon intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, repentance removes the matter of Gods anger and diſpleaſure, fire burns no
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152582:17"/>longer then the fuell feeds it, our ſins are the fuell of his wrath, repentance removes them, and his wrath ceaſeth, namely it is his own gracious covenant, the ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion of the Goſpel, he hath condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned with us, if ye repent, he will be mercifull we owe it to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Goſpel, thus our Repentance prevailes with him.</p>
            <p>Come we to the ſecond particular of this hope that he will repent, thats ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gracious effect of our Repentance, it will cauſe God to repent; a ſtrange work to ſee God repent, Repentance it is for man, and for ſinfull man, God is not as man that he ſhould repent. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.29. Repentance it is but in two caſes, neither incident unto God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, when any thing happens upon our actions which we did not foreſee, God is not miſtaken, known to the Lord are all his works from the beginning.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when we do that which we do not approve, Gods works are all holy and unblameable, why ſhould he repent? and yet we ſee the Scripture uſes this language, <hi>it repented the Lord that he had
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152582:18"/>made man, and it grieved him at his heart.</hi> Gen. 6.6. So it is ſaid in Samuel <hi>it repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord that he had made</hi> Saul <hi>King.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.35. Not that God hath thoſe motions and affections which we find and feel when we repent.</p>
            <p>For firſt Repentance changes us, there is no change in God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Repentance afflicts us, God is not ſubject to any ſorrowfull afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Repentance condemns and blames that action of which we repent, all the actions of God are juſt and holy, and unreproveable; it is a ſpeech after the manner of men, not that God hath the affections of Repentance, but he exerciſes thoſe actions which in man do flow from Repentance; when God changes his deeds and dealing with men, then the Scripture ſaith he repents; Repentance in God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a change in ſome affect of his, no change of his minde, <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith he is ſaid to reverſe his ſentence, but not to alter his Councel; or take it thus, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance hath a double aſpect, firſt, it looks backward to what hath been done, ſo it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152582:18"/>is <hi>Nolle feciſſe,</hi> I wiſh I had not done ſo, this action is not in God, he is never ſorry for what he hath done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Repentance looks forward and ſo it is <hi>Noble ultra facere</hi> I wil do ſo no more, this <hi>God</hi> aſſumes to himſelf. I will puniſh no more; I will change my dealings, bleſs where I curſed, promiſe where I threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yet we muſt not part with this ſweet expreſſion of Gods repenting toward us, we ſee God clothes himſelf with this repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and melting affection, <hi>it repented the Lord becauſe of their groanings,</hi> Judges. 2.18. <hi>He repented according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his mercies,</hi> Pſalm 106.45. So God threatens many Judgements, then adds, the Lord repented of this, it ſhould not be, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.7. See how Gods relenting and reverſing his threatnings, agrees with his repenting.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>in all their afflictions, he was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,</hi> Eſay. 63.9. How doth he ſeem to condole their puniſhments, <hi>She hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Lords hand double for all her ſins,</hi> Iſa. 40.2. How ſhall I give thee up <hi>Ephraim,</hi> my heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled together.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that is another expreſſion of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152582:19"/>Repentance to break off the curſe that was intended, thus God aſſumes Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, if he hath puniſhed, he will ceaſe from puniſhing, if he hath threatned he will cancel his threatnings, if he hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sentence he will reverſe it, he deſires to repent of the evil he hath purpoſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he that repents is angry with all that provoked him to do what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents of, or were helpers, or inſtruments in the doing of it, thus doth God all thoſe that had any hand in afflicting o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his people, he is highly diſpleaſed with them, as a Parent caſts the rod into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fire; he will afflict, thoſe that afflicted his people: thus God threatens <hi>Edom Thou ſhouldeſt not have looked upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day of thy brother, in the day that he became to be a ſtranger,</hi> Obad. 12. verſe: thus Go tells <hi>Abraham, The Nation that ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them I will judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, he that repents of what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath done, will do the quite contrary ſo God repents over his people, hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> affrighted them with threatnings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will refreſh them with promiſes? Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152582:19"/>he afflicted them with puniſhments, he will comfort them with bleſſings, <hi>He hath wounded us, and he will heal us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, a true penitent will vow the contrary, ſo doth God ſwear to them to ſpare them; for this is as the waters of <hi>Noah</hi> unto me; <hi>For as I have ſworn that the waters of</hi> Noah <hi>ſhould no more go over the earth, ſo have I ſworn that I would not be wroth with thee nor rebuke thee,</hi> Iſaiah 54.9.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, a true Penitent will not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do the contrary, but do a great deal more, redeem his former action by a double amendment, ſo God repents of afflicting his people, for a little anger a great deal of love and mercy, <hi>For a ſmall moment have I forſaken thee, but with great mercies will I gather thee, in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wrath I hid my face from thee, but with everlaſting kindneſſes will I have mercy upon thee,</hi> Iſa. 54.7, 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third matter of their hope, is he renewing of his mercies, he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eave a bleſſing behind him, here is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hird benefit, by repenting, it gives us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ope to recover his former mercies, it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152582:20"/>prevails with God, not onely to free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from judgments, but to ſtore us with bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, this good we get by turning an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> repenting, we ſhall not be loſers b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods Judgements and afflictions, it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here graciouſly promiſed, verſe 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>will reſtore to you the years that the Locuſt have eaten, the Canker-worm and the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpiller and the Palmer-worm, my grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Army which I ſent amongſt you,</hi> not onely no more annoyance by them, but yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall regain your loſſes, not feel th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſmart of former Judgements, theſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the welcomes that Repentance finds a Gods hand, it doth not barely ſet us i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſtate we were before, but betters o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> condition: thus the loving father recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Prodigal, <hi>Luk</hi> 15. and not onely pardons him, but embraces him, not on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cloaths him, but adorns him: this is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Superperdium</hi> of mercy, this is the dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Repentance; where he pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, he doth not onely take off hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Judgements, but brings mercy upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them; is this the manner of me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> O Lord, we count it fair favour to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape deſerved puniſhment, but over a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152582:20"/>above to be laden with mercies; and the manner of expreſſion is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is called a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a leaving a bleſſing behind him.</p>
            <p>Firſt to leave a bleſsing, no doubt they meant plenty and abundance, that which the Locuſts had not already devoured; Firſt this ſpeech acknowledges our being undone, and deſert to loſe all; that's one fruit of Repenrance; If we enjoy any comfort it is his goodneſs, a true penitent confeſſeth he hath forfeited all, it is his goodneſſe that he takes it not.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſee how Repentance hath purified and refined their Language; Proſperity, Plenty, the fruits of the earth were our own before, all in <hi>Eſau's</hi> ſtile, <hi>I have enough,</hi> or in <hi>Nabal's, My bread and my fleſh,</hi> it is either Natures bounty, or the fruits of our labour, all of our own acquiring, thus we over poſſeſſe the things of this life, but when we repent the Prophet will teach us to call them as they are, bleſſings from his holy hand, our peace, before it was the wiſdome of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152582:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>the State, or the dread of our enemies, or our riches and ſtrength; but after a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Repentance will teach us to call them as they are, bleſſings from God, and to whom to aſcribe it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſee how Repentance will cauſe us to ſet a right eſtimate upon them, not ſo much to own them, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, as love them as bleſsings, that is to take comfort in them as fruits of his hand, pledges of his favour, ſeals of our Reconciliation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it will point us to the true Author, they are not fortune, but his hand leaves them to us, not our enemies, not the Surpluſſage of a judgement, but he hath commanded a bleſsing for us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is ſaid, leaving a belſſing beind him, What means that? It hath three powers in it, in it are three intimations.</p>
            <p>It ſets out the juſt order of bleſſing, Firſt, favour, then fruit of favour, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Firſt aims at recovering of favour, <hi>Pardon my ſin, O Lord, caſt me not away from thy preſence,</hi> moſt anxious for that after, that it hopes and expects other mercies, Oh a true Penitent priſes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152582:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>Gods favour better then life it ſelf, or the means of life, other means are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, it is an unworthy love to love God for his bleſſings, and for himſelf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſets out the meaſure of bleſſing; Repentance counts it an high favour, though God afflicts us, yet that he doth not conſume us; though the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts come, or any other judgment, and God means to chaſten us, yet it ſhall be in meaſure; it is our comfort, that when he puniſhes, that he remembers mercy not to ſuffer his whole diſpleaſure to riſe, that he puniſhed us in judgment, not in fury, this <hi>Iſaiah</hi> acknowledges, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Except the Lord had left us a ſmall Remnant, we had been as</hi> Sodome; ſo <hi>Jeremy</hi> acknowledges this mercy in the captivity, <hi>That we are not utterly conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med:</hi> So God promiſes <hi>Ezech.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Yet behold, there ſhall be left a remnant, both ſons and daughters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it ſhews the continuance; though he chaſtiſe us, yet he leaves a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, it is a comfort to a Penitent, that God reſerves mercy till afterward, that his anger it is like a Land flood, <hi>non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabit
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152582:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>aetatem,</hi> that he will do us good at the latter end, after our chaſtiſements, as it was a great incouragement, that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> was commanded to purchaſe at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathoth,</hi> fields ſhall be bought, here is the contrary viciſſitude of Gods dealing with the wicked, he may begin in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but he will end in judgements; contrary with his Church, he may begin with chaſtiſements, but it ſhall cloſe up well; he will leave a bleſsing behind him, Job<hi>'s portion, his captivity was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to do them good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, come we to the fourth mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their hope, a meat offering and a drink-offring to the Lord our God, that's a main bleſſing, they hope to recover by their repentance, it is a pregnant prayer, and many particulars in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the end they aim at in ſeeking deliverance from their enemies; that they might appear in his Temple, and worſhip him; if then we ask peace and ſafety to the purpoſe, that we might enjoy opportunities of ſerving of God, let him have the glory, ſo <hi>Zachary</hi> teaches u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Leſſon in the 1. of <hi>Luke,</hi> 74, 75.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152582:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>That we being delivered out of the hands of our enemies might ſerve him without fear, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before him all the dayes of our life,</hi> it troubled <hi>David</hi> that he was excluded the houſe of God, <hi>Paul</hi> teaches us to pray for our Governours, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. That we may live in peace and quietneſſe in all godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and honeſty, peace without piety it is a carnal peace; this made <hi>David</hi> pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem, Our feet ſhall ſtand in thy gates.</hi> Peace is Gods hedge, about his Church, if his ſervice proſper not break down the hedge.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is the fruit of our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to offer meat-offerings, what were the Sacrifices of thanksgiving, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51. I, when we have appealed by Repentance, then our Services and Sacrifices ſhall be accepted, till we be reconciled, all our oblations are abominations, he will not ſmell in our ſolemn Aſſemblies; incenſe is an abomination, but repent, and then God accepts thy offerings, an impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner is as if he bleſſed an idol when he prayes, but the penitent ſhall ſpeed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is the Dedication of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152582:23"/>they hope for a bleſſing behind him; of plenty if they may ſee, they will devote it to his worſhip and ſervice, plenty every man wiſhes for, but wilt thou ſerve God, honour him with thy riches, the failing of this foretells all, becauſe thou ſerveſt not the Lord thy God with gladneſſe of heart for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of all things, therefore thou ſhalt ſerve thine enemies in hunger, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.47, 48.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is an holy care for Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip that it be maintained; God challenged the Jews for it after captivity, the times was not to build the Temple, but to ſtay till they had ſtore, build pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate houſes, let Gods houſe lie waſt, ſee they aim at that, if we may have Gods worſhip, it is all they aim at; brown bread and the Goſpel is good fare.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God ſhall have the glory:</p>
            <p>Secondly not verbal, but with coſt too.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, and not a preſent but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for a laſting worſhip, ſo much of the matter.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the meaſure of hope, who knows; a ſtrange kind of incouragement,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152582:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet ſometimes in Scripture this form is uſed. I find four places, the firſt is <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.8. Who can tell if God will turn and repent, it was the ſpeech of a heathen King to a heathen People, not acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo well with Gods dealings, the ſecond is <hi>Daniel</hi> 4.27. Break of thy ſins it may be a lengthning of thy tranquility; the third is this of <hi>Joel,</hi> the voice of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to the people of God. The fourth is <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.3. Seek the Lord ye meek of the earth, it may be ye ſhall be hidden in the day of the Lords wrath, it is but a may be, though the voice of the Prophet to the heathen people, it is a ſtrange ſpeech ſeeming contrary &amp; inconſiſtent.</p>
            <p>Firſt, with Gods goodneſſe, it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in every good nature to be eaſie to pardon, which of you that are evill know how to forgive; yet the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> much more the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is mercifull.</p>
            <p>Secondly, inconſiſtent with his preſent invitation to Repentance, he preſcribes Repentance, peradventure who preſcribes Phyſick, ſo <hi>Jonas</hi> thought him ready to pardon.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:152582:24"/>
            <p>Thirdly, inconſiſtent with the incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.13. The Prophet reckons up all Gods ſweet Attributes, now ſeems to croſſe all and diſhearten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Repentance, by <hi>quis novit</hi> he will aboundantly padon, <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 54.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it ſeems contrary to his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute covenant and promiſe to pardon penitents, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.21. <hi>If the wicked do that which is right he ſhall live,</hi> it is the Tenor of the Goſpel, what ſhall we think of it, even this promiſe, and even this half promiſe and intimation may be uſefull.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it ſhews the grievouſneſs of ſins, great ſins are hardly pardoned, <hi>Simon Magus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſhews the hope that is left, after ſin our hopes are much weakned.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it ſhews the difficulty of the benefit, we may be in ſuch danger.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it ſhews the uncertainty of temporall freedom.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, it ſhews mercy, and to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done if we cannot challenge it. Here are two things the loweſt ſtep of hope, if we have no more, yet hold this, I will wait and pray, if I cannot get aſſurance.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152582:24"/>
            <p>Secondly, we when we have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods covenant, then we have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to pleade, but <hi>quis novit,</hi> who knows; not according to thy covenant.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:152582:25"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſalm, <hi>78.</hi> verſ. <hi>34.35.36.37</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>When he ſlew them, then they ſought him an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> turned them early, and inquired after God, and they remembred that God wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their ſtrength, and that the high God wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Redeemer; nevertherleſs they di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but flatter him with their mouth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and diſſembled with him in their tongue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for their heart was not whole with him neither continued they ſtedfaſt in his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pſalm;
<note place="margin">Ingratiarum actione pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica.</note> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may term it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pſalm of record or a <hi>Pſalm</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bring to remembrance, 'tis an holy Pane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gyrick or a ſong for the whole Nation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> people of the <hi>Jews;</hi> a ſolemn recitall o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the many memorable paſſages in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Common-Wealth from their firſt ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152582:25"/>and it hath been the wiſdom of Kingdoms &amp; Common-Wealths to have their <hi>Chrongraphos,</hi> thoſe that ſhould record and regiſter the ſeverall paſſages and affairs of their State, to keep upon record their beginnings and foundation, their Acts and Monuments, the good and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll events that have be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ided them, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the wiſdom of God authorized and imployed his ſacred Penmen and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries to inroll and regiſter up the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erall paſſages of the Church, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ansmit them to poſterity, in particular, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſides thoſe ſacred Annals of his Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontained in the Hiſtoricall books of Scripture, the holy Ghoſt hath purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y framed, ſome more ſummary and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endious, but yer full and perfect relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns of the affairs of his Church, and this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kewiſe compoſed and framed into ſongs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd pſalms, to make them more fit carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge for memory, and that by the pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe of them they might ſink more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeply into their hearts, &amp; more ſtrongly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffect them. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> after all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons, and commemorations made to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople, 32. <hi>Deut.</hi> Of Gods dealings with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152582:26"/>them &amp; their carriage towards him, at l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he compoſed a ſong, and it to the peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and commends it to poſterity as a laſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Monument for all generations, thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> poets among the heathen (whom <hi>Tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Paul,</hi> calls their Prophets) had <hi>carmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeculario,</hi> their ſtate ſongs compriſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the affairs of their Common-Wealt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anſwerable was that ſweet ſinger of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> the Prophet <hi>David</hi> is ſtudious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> frame ſuch ſacred ſongs; as firſt this pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent Pſalm, ſo again the 89. Then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 105.106.107. All publick Pſalms a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſongs of commemoration; <hi>David</hi> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that which the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſpeaks o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chap. the 5.1. <hi>I will ſing to my well-b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loved a ſong of my beloved touching b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vineyard,</hi> I termed it a Pſalm of record or of commemoration, &amp; ſo it is, if we re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpect the materialls of which it conſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tis a recitall of Gods gracious dealing towards his people and of their ungrac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous dealings towards him again; but ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I find another name given by the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſt; 'tis called Maſchil in the title <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Pſalm, and that name reſpects th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> end and purpoſe of it. Maſchill is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:152582:26"/>Pſalm to give inſtruction; 'tis not onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtoricall but Doctrinal, even theſe Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oricall parts of Scripture are not onely Gods day book to tell us what hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before, but they muſt be to us a Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ook to teach us what we muſt do, 'tis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot onely a Pſalm to bring to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance which is the title of 38. and 70. Pſalms, but Maſchil a Pſalm for inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, when he commemorates his ancient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ercies to their fore-fathers, thats Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hill a Pſalm of inſtruction, <hi>we have heard with our ears O Lord, and our fathers have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old us, what works thou didſt in their days, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the times of old,</hi> what is the inſtruction of that, it ſhould teach us confidence in God; Pſalm 7.1. That they might ſet their hope in God. When he commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates ancient deliverances from perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and enemies, thats <hi>Maſchill</hi> a Pſalm for inſtruction, to look for the like deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances from him in our dangers and diſtreſſes, many a time did he deliver them, then deliver us amongſt the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen, Pſalm. 106.477. When he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorates the wicked and ungracious courſes of their forefathers, thats <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chill</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:152582:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>a Pſalm of inſtruction, to avoid thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fathers ſins, not to be as their forefather a ſtubborn and rebellious generation that ſet not their heart aright, and whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpirit was not ſtedfaſt with God, and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inſtruction was not onely for them, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the after times of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould make a profitable uſe of the former times, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it reaches to us Chriſtians; Saint <hi>Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> tells us that the times of the <hi>Jews</hi> concer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us Chriſtians, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Whatſoever things were written before time, were writ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ten for our learning,</hi> and again, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> He acquaints them what befell the <hi>Jews</hi> then adds verſe the 6. Theſe things were written for our examples, to the inten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we ſhould not luſt as they alſo luſted, and then telling them of the Judgments tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> befell the <hi>Jews,</hi> in the 11. Verſe he ſaith, theſe things hapned to them for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and they were written for our admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nirion, ſo then this Pſalm ſets forth the great diſobedience, and ſtubborneſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> under Gods govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it upbraids them with forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his mercies.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:152582:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Secondly, it objects unto them their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>proficiency and untractableneſſe even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y miracles.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it reminds them of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane abuſe of his patience.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it reproves them for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>corrigibleneſſe by his chaſtiſements.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, it ſhews them withal the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe and unſoundneſſe of their hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icall Repentance.</p>
            <p>The Text it contains this laſt, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake the purpoſe of it to be Gods cenſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd reproof of the <hi>Jews</hi> unworthy Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance, and in it obſerve theſe two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ſeverall Acts of their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the many defects and faults <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f their Repentance.</p>
            <p>The firſt, will ſhew us, how farr they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent in the practiſe of Repentance.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, will diſcover their fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings, how much they came ſhort of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue ſpiritual ſaving Repentance.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Acts of Repentance, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere they performed, they are four.</p>
            <p>Firſt ſeeking they ſought him.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:152582:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Secondly, returning, they returned.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, inquiring they inquired ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> after God.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Remembring, they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that God was their ſtrong rock, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the high God their Redeemer; theſe as the four Acts and exerciſes of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſuch as they were.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Text ſets out the defect of their Repentance, how much they fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it, they likewiſe are four.</p>
            <p>The firſt defect and fault of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance twas untimely, delayed Repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, thats implied in this word when no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> till ſuch a time, then, not till then.</p>
            <p>Secondly, twas an inforced Repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, not ingenuous and voluntarily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken; twas extorted by plagues, the repented when they were under the ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay under the ſword, twas when he ſle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, twas an unſound Repentanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not true and ſincere, but fained and act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> onely, 'twas a flattering and lying Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, they flattered him with their mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and they lyed unto him with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tongues.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:152582:28"/>
            <p>Fourthly, 'twas a momentany, tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, unſettled, unconſtant Repentance not firm and laſting, their heart was not right with him, neither were they ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in his Covenant, theſe foure faults.</p>
            <p>Firſt, untimely and backward.</p>
            <p>Secondly, inforc't and extorted.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, unſound and diſlembling.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, vaniſhing and unconſtant.</p>
            <p>Theſe are uſually linked together, one draws on the other, theſe four twiſts makes up <hi>Eſays</hi> Cart rope of ſin.</p>
            <p>Firſt he that puts off &amp; procraſtinates, and delayes his repentance, he will never bethink himſelf of it, or ſet himſelf to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it, till ſome judgement awakens him and conſtrains him to it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he that repents not but by conſtraint, and when he is under the laſh, uſually, if he look not well to it, it will be but a ſhew of Repentance and outward humiliation, and no better.</p>
            <p>And then laſtly, unſound Repentance will never prove laſting Repentance, he will ſoon be weary of it, and return to his former wont again,</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152582:29"/>
            <p>Come we to the firſt, briefly take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> view of the Acts and exerciſes of their Repentance; ſeeking, returning, inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after god, and remembring of him. Actions all of them in their own nature good, all of them if rightly performed penitential Acts, good ingredients into Repentance.</p>
            <p>Firſt put them together, they are ſuch acts as accompany Repentance, and will afford us a double meditation.</p>
            <p>The firſt meditation ariſes by way of ſuppoſition.</p>
            <p>The ſecond by a direct poſition.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by way of ſuppoſition; theſe actions of ſeeking, returning, enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, remembring, being acts, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and exerciſes of Repentance, they all ſuppoſe the quite contrary actions that accompany our ſinning, as thus.</p>
            <p>Firſt, when we repent we ſet our ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſeek God, therefore when we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin we part with God, repentance that's a ſeeking, therefore ſin and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that's a loſing of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in Repentance there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to God, 'tis a work of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152582:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore in our ſinning there is a departing from God, and a forſaking of God, that's more, forſaking is more then a loſing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly in Repentance there is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after God; therefore in a courſe of ſinne and before we repent we never think of him, but ſleight and neglect him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in repentance there is a remembring, there is a remembring of God and of his mercies, therefore by ſin we do not onely not actually think of him, but we grow into forgetfulneſſe of God, we have no remembrance of him, theſe four evil effects of ſin, take notice of them by ſinning againſt God.</p>
            <p>Firſt we loſe him, nay we forſake him, nay we never ſo much as think of him, nay we remove him out of our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries we utterly forget him, here's the condition of a ſtubborn and a wilfull ſinner, a man that lives and lies in ſin, he doth wretchedly caſt off all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, rejects and abandons him; though he may have ſome vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing notions of God, yet to all good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes he is an arrant Atheiſt, without
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152582:30"/>God in the world, no intereſt in him, no effectual cogitation of him, this eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the Scripture puts upon a wicked people.</p>
            <p>Firſt it calls them forſaken of God, <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſinfull Nation, they have forſaken the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 1-4. <hi>So your fathers have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me,</hi> Jer. 16.11. as Saints are a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Seekers, ſo theſe are a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of forſakers.</p>
            <p>Secondly the Scripture calls them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from God, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.4. <hi>They have departed from me with a whoriſh heart: David</hi> deſcribes a wicked man, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 18.21. <hi>I have not wickedly departed from my God,</hi> there is a wicked departure, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle forewarns them of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Take heed of an evil heart, to depart from the living God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Scripture calls them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volters, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.6. <hi>The children of Iſrael have deeply revolted, they are grievous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volters, Ier.</hi> 6.28. The Scripture repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents them, as thruſting God from them. <hi>Cauſe the Holy One of Iſrael to ceaſe from before us,</hi> Iſa. 30.11. and for the matter of inquiry or thought,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152582:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>or remembrance of God, the Scripture makes this the mark, and guiſe and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a wicked man, to lay aſide all thoughts of God, <hi>the wicked through the pride of his countenance, will not ſeek after God: God is not in all his thoughts,</hi> Pſalm 10.4.5. God is far above out of his thoughts, he tuſhes at the name of him; <hi>Pharaoh ſaid that which every wicked man thinks, who is the Lord, I know not the Lord,</hi> Exod. 5.2. Ye that forget God; 'tis a wicked mans deſcription, all the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that forget God; it ſhould beget ſome ſad thoughts in us were there nothing elſe in ſin, no other miſchievous conſequences following it, it ſhould ſtrike upon the heart of obſtinate ſinners; what while I live in ſin am I no better then an Atheiſt? Is this the fruit of all my courſes, do they utterly eſtrainge me from God? I loſe him and the thoughts of him, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him; yes that thou doſt; thou mayeſt go for a Chriſtian, and be reckoned amongſt the people of God, and ſeem to a vow him and to be acquainted with him, but while thou liveſt in thine impenitency, thou art wholy eſtranged
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152582:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>from him even the children of God, in their failings and infitmities they finde theſe ſad effects partially, and in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; not a fault that they commit, but it ſets them off ſome degrees from God; it weakens their hold of him, they loſe him in part; it dumbs their thoughts of him, it dulls their remembrance of him; but a wicked man in an impenitent courſe, hath all theſe miſchiefs in extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; thats the firſt meditation, their ſuppoſition.</p>
            <p>A ſecond meditation is by direct inference and poſition, that true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance will inforce upon us a ſeeking of God whom by ſin we have loſt, a return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God whom we have forſaken, an inquiring after God whom we have neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, a remembring of God whom we have forgotten.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it will put us to a ſeeking &amp; thats the firſt act of eſtimation, it values that it ſeeks; if we count it as good loſt as found, no great matter whether we hit or miſſe there will be no ſeeking; if we meet with it by chance; well &amp; good, but lightly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued, is but lightly ſought for; <hi>it muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:152582:31"/>precious pearl that the Merchant ſeeks for, Math.</hi> 13.45. When we come to this reſolution, if we miſſe of Gods favour we are undone, if I find it again, I am made for ever, then we ſeek as we ſhould, becauſe we value it as we ſhould, <hi>thy favour is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then life it ſelf,</hi> Pſalm 63.3. See how <hi>David</hi> valued it, <hi>be not ſilent to me, leaſt if thou be ſilent to me, I become like them that go down into the pit,</hi> Pſalm 28.1. It is death to miſſe him; better then life to find him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it will put us to a ſeeking, thats an act of diligence, ſearch implies labour, and anxiety, and all poſſible indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, ſuch are the ſeekings of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; not a few flugiſh wiſhes, but it will be active and induſtrious, <hi>it lights up the candle and ſweeps the houſe,</hi> Luke 15.8. A penitent ſoul will give no reſt to it ſelf, till it have recovered God and his favour thats the ſeeking God will accept, <hi>ye ſhall ſeek and find me, when ye ſhall ſearch with all your hearts,</hi> Jer. 29.13. Not the laſie ſeeking of the ſpouſe, <hi>In my bed by night I ſought him, but I did not find him but when ſhe gets up into the ſtreets amongſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152582:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>the watch men, then at laſt ſhe finds him,</hi> thats the firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it will put us to a returning, it will make us tread over all our ſteps, and ſtrainings and wanderings from God with ſorrow, and undo what we have done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; do the quite contrary, it will make us reſolve with the Church in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.7. <hi>I will go and return to my firſt huſband, for then it was better for me then now,</hi> ſo again Hoſea 6.1. <hi>Come let us return unto the Lord,</hi> it is called a converſion, a full and pregnant word, not a meer averſion from ſin, Repentance it is not a meer ceſſation and giving over what we did before, and then reſt, a man thats out of his way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers not himſelf by a meer ſtop and ſtay, no, he muſt go back again.</p>
            <p>Secondly, 'tis not a meer diverſion, give over this ſinfull courſe and turn into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I will be no more prodigal, but I will fall into ſome other carnall or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall practiſe.</p>
            <p>But 'tis Thirdly, a full converſion, that brings him to the firſt point from which he ſtrayed; thus <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> 4.1. Directs, <hi>If thou wilt return, O Iſrael, ſaith the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152582:32"/>Lord, return unto me:</hi> it brings a man round about, makes him a quite other man, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance it will put us to inquiring, thats a buſie work, inquiring and ſearching di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 1.10. Puts them together, our Saviour calls it; ſeeking, and asking, and knocking, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with others that can direct us, thus the penitents in the Acts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. Acts. 2.7. enquired of <hi>Peter</hi> and John, <hi>Men and brethren what ſhall we do?</hi> help and direct us, ſo the penitent Jayler, Acts 16.30. <hi>Sirs what muſt I do to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi> the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſhews them this duty, ſtand in the paths, and ask for the old paths, where is the good way; and <hi>Iſaiah</hi> quickens them to this inquiry, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 21.11.12. <hi>Bids them enquire of the watchman, and what ſaith he, if ye will inquire, inquire, that is do it, and do it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, do it to ſome purpoſe; enquire of the guides that God hath ſet up. Enquire of thoſe that have ſtrayed and wandered, and loſt him &amp; now have found him; what courſe took they, and it muſt be early, take the wings of the morning; early beginings may do much.</hi> Iſaiah gives us this Item, <hi>the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152582:33"/>watchman ſaith the morning comes, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the night, if yee will enquire, enquire, returne and come, the dayes are ſhort, the morning ſpends, the night haſtens, early ſeekers ſeldome miſſe, but late begianings moſt commonly fall ſhort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly. Repentance it will quicken our memories, they remembred that God was their rock, and the high God their Redeemer, it will make us recall to mind all the goodneſſe of God towards us, thus the revolting Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when ſhe bethinks her ſelfe of returning to God. She recounts how well 'twas with her when ſhe kept her ſelfe to him. So the returning prodigall, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. He remembered the plenty of his fathers houſe, this remembering of Gods grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dealings with us hath great force in the work of repentance.</p>
            <p>Firſt. It will upbraide us for our baſe unthankfulneſſe, <hi>Doe yee thus reward the Lord yee fooliſh Nation, is not he thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that hath bought thee, hath not he made thee and eſtabliſhed thee, Deut.</hi> 32.6.</p>
            <p>Secondly. It melts our hearts into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe and ſorrow, oh, the love of Chriſt conſtraines us.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:152582:33"/>
            <p>Thirdly. It incourages and puts heart into our repentance, I will remmber the years of the right hand, we have ſeen the 4 acts in which their repentance conſiſted, now follows the ſecond thing obſervable, thats the failings and defects of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance that made it unacceptable and they were 4.</p>
            <p>Firſt. It was untimely.</p>
            <p>Secondly. It was extorted and inforced.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. It was falſe and hipocriticall.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. Twas momentary and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant and fickle</p>
            <p>Firſt. Twas untimely, a delaid repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, they ſinned, kept not his covenant <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 78.10. Again, they ſinned yet more, <hi>verſe</hi> 17. ſtill they went on again, for all this they ſinned ſtill, <hi>verſe.</hi> 22. wheeled off and delaied, and ſet back their repentance. Even this is a malignant cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, breeds a great flaw and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh in our repentance, the late date it beares, oh repentance would be a timely a ſpeedy, and an early work.</p>
            <p>Tis preſently done, as ſoon as we have ſinned, ſo, <hi>ratione officij,</hi> by the law of right and reaſon, a man is bound to be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152582:34"/>ſorry as ſoone as we have done evill, tis Gods Dove and he demands it preſently; even in lending, <hi>Solomon</hi> bids us not put off till to morrow, much more in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy debts.</p>
            <p>Secondly. Tis good repenting betimes <hi>ratione incerti,</hi> doe it while thou maiſt doe it, while we have time, in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſow thy ſeed, thou knoweſt not what a day will bring forth, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.6. here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after repentance may be hid from thine eyes; we all pretend our reſolutions are to repent, we grant we muſt repent, and reſolve to repent before we dy, be it ſo, be ſure thou repent before thou dy, and then thou muſt retent ſpeedily, for time to come is moſt hazardous; uncertainty, the Jews have a rule, he that vows to doe any thing before he dye, he muſt doe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeedily, becauſe he is not certain whether he ſhall live till to morrow, and then his vow tis broken, and he muſt anſwer for it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. Tis good repenting betimes, <hi>ratione facilitatis,</hi> timely repentance is the moſt kindly, and gentle, and eaſie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, a wound is beſt taken when it is green, defer to dreſſe it, and it will ranc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152582:34"/>and feſter, a bone is beſt put into joynt as ſoon as it is out, neglect it any time it will hardly keep in; repentance is the phyſick of the ſoule, and phyſick ye know is beſt taken in the morning, thus <hi>Peter</hi> went out preſently. <hi>When I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed I ſmote upon my thigh, Jer.</hi> 31.19.</p>
            <p>Firſt. This is the failing of theſe men repentance, tis all dilatories, put it off as long as may be, it ſhews they took little pleaſure in it.</p>
            <p>Secondly. They came unwillingly to it, as a Beare to the ſtake, you muſt fetch him about with a ring in his noſe, not ſet to it by any inward principle of grace, but upon other inducements, or inforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments rather; but yet there is one word in the text, which ſeemes to ſet a timely date upon their repentance, 'tis ſaid they enquired early after God, how can this ſtand with this procraſtinating, when <hi>mane properabunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they haſtened, <hi>diluculo veniebant,</hi> ſo others by day break, true, true, all this takes not off the charge and imputation of late repentance.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:152582:35"/>
            <p>Firſt. It is an holy ſcorn and deriſion of their ſlow and ſluggiſh returning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. Yes, yes, after ſo much time waſted and mercies abuſed, and provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions multiplyed, now you beſtir your ſelves, is this your early return to God, ſo ſhaming their backwardneſs in this need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full duty.</p>
            <p>Secondly. The Scripture even in the ſame place it upbraids ſinners with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies, yet then uſes this term of early ſeeking, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Becauſe when I have called yee refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand and no man regarded,</hi> verſe 28. <hi>Therefore then they ſhall call upon me, but I will not anſwer, they ſhall ſeek me early, but they ſhall not find me,</hi> here are two extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, very late, nay too late, and yet ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch converſations, they have an early and a late, or rather, and an early, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening and morning.</p>
            <p>Firſt. They have <hi>veſper tinum culpae,</hi> look at the time of their ſinning, oh 'tis very lare ere they repented, all the day long and they never thought of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly. There is <hi>matutinum penae,</hi> the morning of their puniſhment, when
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152582:35"/>Gods Judgements break in upon them then they beſtir themſelves; take their day of ſinning, ſo 'tis <hi>veſper,</hi> take their day of ſuffering ſo tis, <hi>mane, ſero quoad culpam, cito quoad penam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or thirdly. They ſeek and inquire, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yet very late, thats early, or <hi>mane,</hi> when one awakens, the ſluggards morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when he breakes off ſleepe, that may be at noon or night in true computation, ſecutity layes a ſinner in a deep ſleep, when Gods hands awakens him, thats morning, till then they are aſleep, thats the firſt fault, untimely.</p>
            <p>A ſecond defect of their repentance is that 'twas inforct, <hi>cum occideret,</hi> when he ſlew them and his judgements fell upon them, then they bethought themſelves and turned unto him, thats a ſecond ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant circumſtance, that marres much of their repentance, till then they never thought of him, many other times there were that would have become their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, much better then this, when he ſlew them and fell upon them with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying judgement.</p>
            <p>Firſt. <hi>Quando pecarunt,</hi> as ſoon as they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152582:36"/>had ſinned, had they any grace they ſhould have repented, I told you before repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is preſently done as ſoon as we have ſinned, God calls all that delays it, fools, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Yee fooles how long will ye love fooliſhneſſe,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian, Deus dedicavit penitentiam in paradiſo,</hi> ſo, the time as ſoon as ever <hi>Adam</hi> had ſinned, God ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond him to repent; wiſedome and grace would have us doe ſo, thus tis with <hi>David</hi> when he numbred the people, preſently his heart ſmore him, he ſaw his fault and ſorrowed for it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, well, ſuppoſe they took not the firſt time, there were more interme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate times before he came to ſlay them, <hi>quando, benefacit iis,</hi> when he did good to them, that ſhould reclaim them, they ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and yet he ceaſed not from bleſſing them, they murmured and yet he bleſſed them, they tempted him and yet he fed them, they would poſe his power whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he could fetch water out of the rock, and he did it for them. O thats high time for Repentance, when Gods goodneſſe wreſtles and ſtrives with our wickedneſſe, and would over come us, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152582:36"/>it deeply upon impenitent ſinners, tells them it makes them inexcuſable, R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m. 2.4. <hi>Or deſpiſeſt thou the riches of his goodneſſe and forbearance, and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, not knowing that the goodneſſe of God leadeth thee to Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, there is another time when they ſhould have repented, <hi>quando invitavit,</hi> when by the Miniſtery of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> he found fault with their ſins and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them to repent, that ſure is a juſt time for us to repent, when Gods word calls us to Repentance; 'tis that which <hi>Chriſt</hi> commends in the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> Mat. 12.41. <hi>The men of Nineveh ſhall riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with this generation, they repented at the preaching of Jonah;</hi> no ſooner did God diſpatch a Prophet to them to call them to repentance, but they yielded preſently; 'tis that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> takes comfort, in the matter of his converſion, Act. 26.19. <hi>I was not diſobedient to the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viſion,</hi> 'twas that alſo that commanded the converſion of thoſe penitents, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>When they heard this they were pricked to the heart,</hi> one Sermon of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> reclaimed them preſently in the audience
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152582:37"/>One look of <hi>Chriſt</hi> took <hi>Peter;</hi> the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of the word is the great ſanctified inſtrument to work us to Repentance, 'tis a great aggravation to our impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to live unconverted under that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, yet there were other impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities that in all reaſon they ſhould have to repent, though they ſlighted the former, thats <hi>quando caſtigavit,</hi> when he did viſite their ſins with more moderate and fatherly chaſtiſements, we know God had his ferulaes, and rods, and fatherly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections with which he did viſite them. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.2.3. <hi>He humbled thee with hunger and drought, want of bread and water,</hi> the wilderneſſe in which he led them, was a School of afflictions, and therefore in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to that, afflictions ate called a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying into the wilderneſſe, <hi>I will bring her into the wilderneſſe and ſpeak comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably into her,</hi> Hoſea 2.14. 'Tis the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all way that God takes with us, when his word alone will do us no good, to write our leſſons on our back with his rod, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity makes us wanton, afflictions ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times hunt us in and bring us before
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152582:37"/>him; ſickneſſe and poverty, and loſſes and other uncomfortable events, they are uſuall means to reclaim 'us. <hi>Hoſea</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares afflictions to an hedge of thorns, <hi>Behold I will hedge up thy way with thorns, Hoſea</hi> 2.6. So that we ſhall have little liſt to break out, thus was <hi>Manaſſes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, captivity and impriſonment wrought him to Repentance. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.12. <hi>VVhen he was in affliction he ſought the Lord his God, and humbled himſelf greatly before the God of his fathers,</hi> 'twas <hi>Luthers</hi> ſpeech. <hi>Schola Crucis,</hi> 'tis <hi>Schola Lucis,</hi> and it is the great aggravation of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed King <hi>Ahaz</hi> in the time of his diſtreſſe that he did treſpaſſe yet more againſt the Lord, this is that King <hi>Ahaz,</hi> thats his brand, as if ſhould ſay here is a ſinner that afflictions will not tame; 'tis to great purpoſe that <hi>Solomon</hi> adviſes us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.11. my Son deſpiſe not the chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord, gentle corrections muſt not be deſpiſed nor ſlighted; and <hi>David</hi> his Father counted it an happy thing to get good by ſuch chaſtiſiings, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 94.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the Man whom thou chaſteneſt O Lord, and teacheſt him out of thy Law:</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:152582:38"/>He ſhewes it will prevent this ſame acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>That thou mayeſt give him reſt from the dayes of adverſity, untill th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pit be digged for the wicked.</hi> Happy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement that prevents ſlaying, to doe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iſay</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Iſay</hi> 26.16. <hi>Lord, in trouble have they viſited thee; they poured out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> prayer when thy chaſtening was upon them.</hi> No, this wrought not with them, <hi>quan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> caſtigauit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then here is the unworthy ſervile baſeneſſe of their repentance, no time would ſerve but <hi>quando occidet,</hi> when he ſlew them, never till their heads were o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the block; yea this is <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, he ſtood out many a ſtroak, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when it came to a deſtruction, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeekes to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Oh I have ſinned, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> me from this death only. We condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and wonder at it here, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and yet upon due examination we ſhall find it the caſe of many of us take it firſt either more collectively, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> largely, for our nationall repentance.</p>
            <p>Or Secondly, more privatly and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonally for each Man's particular.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let us look abroad not to cenſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:152582:38"/>and deſcant upon other Mens eſtates, but yet we may ſoberly conſider the ſins of the times, and lay them to heart; have we not paſſed all the former quandos, the ſeaſons of repentance with ſmall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Not when we ſinned, God knows many ſins ſtand upon the ſcore uncanceld.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Not when he bleſſed us with deliverances, with peace, plenty, and freedome from annoyances, yet ſmall fruits upon it <hi>Edentibus beneficiis ingrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Not when he hath by his word invited to repentance, nay, that <hi>Manna</hi> comes out at our noſtrills, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to loath it, yee begin to queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God ſpeakes by us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Not when he hath chaſt'ned us in meaſure, ſhot off warning peeces, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then murthering Cannons, commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and plagues, and unnaturall diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, we deſpiſe thoſe chaſtiſements.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, When he comes to ſlay us, then we will bethink our ſelves, when the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is in a light fire, and invaſions of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, or inteſtine rebellions begin to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152582:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſtroy us, then tis to be hoped we will repent.</p>
            <p>Secondly. Let us take it more private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perſonally, and then asks your hearts what time you ſet for your repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; tis <hi>cum occidet;</hi> when we are on our death beds, and no hope of life; when God ſends his laſt executioner to cut us off from the Land of the living, then we reſolve to repent, well, tis poſſible you may do ſo, <hi>depoenitentia non deſperandum quem patientia Dei ſinit vivere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet conſider firſt. Tis <hi>infamia peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae,</hi> here is a brand ſet upon it by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Tis <hi>incerta, dubia,</hi> there is ſmall incouragment the ſcripture gives to it, rather rejects it, ſee what enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment ſuch ſeekers are promiſed to find at Gods hand <hi>Prov.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.24. <hi>Becauſe I have called and ye refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand and no man regarded it, verſe</hi> 26. <hi>I will alſo laugh at your calamity, I will mock when your feare comes, when diſtreſſe and anguiſh comes upon you.</hi> verſe 28. <hi>Then they ſhall call upon me, but I will not anſwer, they ſhall ſeek me early, but they ſhall
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152582:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>not find me,</hi> ſee what incouragement ſuch ſeekers have.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, 'tis <hi>ſuſpicioſa penitentia,</hi> there is great cauſe to ſuſpect the good of ſuch repentance, which is forc'd from us, <hi>cum occideret</hi> when the feare of death ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe that luſt that reigned in him is imp't and forc'd back by his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, 'tis like the ſap of a Tree in winter weather, all ſhrunk to the root, ſorrow, and ſickneſſe, and any great affliction, 'tis like Winter weather, it imps the branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, hinders our corruption from ſprouting and ſo we think 'tis dead, but the root holds life and ſap, warm weather, proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity will make it ſpring again like <hi>Jobs</hi> trees, <hi>chap.</hi> 14.8, 9. through the heate of the weather they will bud.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the feare of death, or any ſore affliction, we may take our ſelves to be mortified, becauſe afflictions will juſtle out temptations, a Man laid on his ſick Bed will have little liſt then to entertain the temptations of ſinfull pleaſure, he hath loſt his relliſh of them for a time, as ſick men can finde no ſweetneſſe in meats
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152582:40"/>(which otherwiſe they delight in) becauſe their taſt is for a time imbittered, let them recover health, and they will fall to againe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in ſickneſſe many take them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves mortified, not becauſe ſin is weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in them, but nature is infeebled, that withdraws her ſtrength, by which ſin was active; recover nature, and ſin will reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as a graft in a Tree, let the Tree ſpring, and that will ſpring too; 'tis not the body of ſin thats mortified, but the body of nature, that is infeebled, put not thy converſion then upon hazardous adventures, ſtay not till he come to ſlay thee by death, 'tis an infamous, 'tis an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, 'tis a ſuſpitious repentance, thou maiſt be miſtaken in it.</p>
            <p>Come we to a third defect of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance thats falſeneſſe and diſſembling, it was a flattering, unſound, hypocriticall repentance. Nevertheleſſe they did flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him with their mouths, and they lyed unto him with their tongues, all their converſion and turning unto God, 'twas but flattery and falſehood, and this flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and falſhood will appeare.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:152582:40"/>
            <p>Firſt in their profeſſions. Secondly in their promiſes, flattering profeſſions, and falſe promiſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt. Flattery is ſeen in profeſſion, firſt a flatterer will profeſſe a great eſteem of goodneſſe and worth in the perſon whom he applyes himſelfe to; ready to aſcribe much unto him, ſo did theſe hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low converts in their affliction, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged God was their rock and ſtrength, and the high God their redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, thus the <hi>Herodians</hi> flattered Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.16. Maſter we know that thou art true, and teacheſt the way of God in truth, and regards no mans perſon, Chriſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers them, why tempt ye me ye Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, ſuch are the ſoothings of unſound repentance when afflictions preſſes us, O then we will acknowledge God and his goodneſs, as <hi>Benadad</hi> did with the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> oh the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are mercifull Kings, but yet falſe and trecherous for all their profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly. Flattery is ſeen in profeſſion of great love and affections, <hi>Judah's</hi> his kiſſe, a profeſſion of great love, as if Chriſt were dear to him, ſuch profeſſions
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152582:41"/>Hypocriticall repentance will make un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affliction; ſuch love <hi>Ziba</hi> ſhewes to <hi>David,</hi> profeſſed great love and loyalty to him, the <hi>Jewes</hi> had ſuch blandiſhments to Gods word, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 29.13. <hi>That they drew nere him with their mouth, and with their lips did honour him, in our extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> who but God and Chriſt are in our mouthes, then we ſeeme much to affect them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. Flattery is ſeen in profeſſion of ſorrow for any offence, a diſſembler to eſcape his due deſerts will confeſſe all, and profeſſe great ſorrow for former of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, thus did railing <hi>Shimei</hi> to <hi>David</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.18. Oh who ſo ſorry for his offences, who ſo ſubmiſſe in confeſſing it, and ſuch profeſſions an Hypocrite under the laſh will make to God, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> when thunder and lightning were about their ears, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.19. Oh we have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in asking a King, beſides all our other ſins, theſe are there flattering profeſſions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as they flattered in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, ſo they were falſe in their promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, repentance will make vowes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and ſo will this falſe and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152582:41"/>repentance abound in promiſes, aske <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> if God ſpare thee this time, wilt thou let <hi>Iſrael</hi> goe? O yes, no longer ſtay, an Hypocrite will bribe God with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, ſpare me this one time, yet all falſe, here obſerve a double falſeneſſe, falſe in intention, ſay what he never meanes, his tongue contradicts his head.</p>
            <p>Secondly, falſe in performances, he never makes good what he ſays, <hi>David</hi> calls it lying fained obedience, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 63.3. <hi>Through the greatneſſe of thy power ſhall thine enemies yeild fained obedience to theſe falſe and counterfeit:</hi> So then in that theſe <hi>Jews</hi> were thus falſe and fraudulent in their repentance, it will diſcover to us the dangerous condition of this ſin of hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſee the guilt of Hypocriſie, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then faile it will counterfeite and act any duty, though never ſo unacceptable, as repentance is, no duty in religion goes downe ſo hard with hypocriſy as repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, repentance is a ſhameing duty, a Penitent muſt confeſſe and acknowledge he hath ſinned, take ſhame and confeſſion to himſelfe, cry out with the Leper I am
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152582:42"/>uncleane, now Hypocrites are <hi>animalia gloriae,</hi> all for their credit and reputation, in matter of opinion they are in no error, <hi>quod volumus ſanctum eſt. Joh.</hi> 9.40. what are we ignorant and blind alſo, in matter of converſation they are without ſpot or wrinckle, you are they which juſtifie your ſelves before men, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.14. 'Tis hard to bring them to acknowledge either errour or fault, but yet if it ſtand for their turn they will even act a penitents part, and confeſſe and recant and ſeem to be ſorry for ſin, ſo did <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and King <hi>Saul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, See the pertinacy and obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of hypocriſie, 'twill act and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, and never give over, no not in the greateſt affliction, <hi>cum occideret,</hi> when Gods hand is in ſlaying them, yet then they will counterfeit, neither mercies, not miracles, nor chaſtiſements, nor plagues will alter or change them, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 26.10. <hi>Let favour be ſhewed to him, yet he will not learn righteouſneſſe,</hi> nay let Gods hand be lifted up, yet they will not ſee it; of all other ſins the hypocrite is the moſt hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and incorrigible, afflictions have
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152582:42"/>brought home prophane ſinners, but an Hypocrite will ſtand to that too, either accuſe God for afflicting him, or diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blingly accuſe himſelf, like ſome deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate cutpurſe, that will ſteal and pilfer in the Seſſions houſe or at the Gallows.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, See the bruitiſh and ſtupid ſottiſhneſſe of hypocriſie, 'twill not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undertake to deceive men, but God alſo, think to mock him with flatteries and lies, as <hi>Ahaz,</hi> how did he cover his infidelity, Oh he would not tempt God, what ſaith <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 7.13. <hi>Is it a ſmall thing to weary men, but will you weary my God alſo,</hi> an Hypocrite will not onely faulter with men, ſeek to delude the world, <hi>but they are lying children to God, Iſaiah</hi> 30.9. Thus <hi>Peter</hi> chargeth <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> that they lyed not to men, but to the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.4. Thus <hi>Iſaiah</hi> brings in the Hypocrites of his time, boaſting even to God of their hypocriticall ſervice and devotion, <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have we faſted and thou ſeeſt it not, wherefore have we afflicted our ſouls and thou takeſt no knowledge? Iſaiah</hi> 58.3. Indeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites are in truth ſecret Atheiſts, they
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152582:43"/>turn the glory of God into an Idoll, ſo hoping to put him off with vizards and counterfeits, worſe then <hi>Jacob</hi> towards <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac,</hi> God can neither ſee, nor feele, nor find out their mockeries, thats the third, the falſeneſſe of their repentance.</p>
            <p>Come we to the fourth defect of their repentance and converſion; it was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary and unconſtant, their hearts were not right with him, verſe 37. <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were they ſtedfaſt in his covenant.</hi> and this clauſe comes in as proofe of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, tis a conviction of their unſound and Hypocriticall repentance, and here is a double conviction by which an Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite may judge of himſelfe, their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance was falſe and fained.</p>
            <p>Firſt becauſe twas not hearty, true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is hearty repentance if the heart be wanting tis counterfeit and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall, their heart was not right with him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe 'twas not laſting and durable, they were not ſtedfaſt in his covenant.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Twas hypocriticall becauſe twas not cordiall, and hearty, how was it not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152582:43"/>hearty, were they not in earneſt, was it meer outſide, acted, pretended repentance tis likely not, theirs a double hypocriſy.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Formall and expreſſe, when he that acts it, intends onely to counterfeit, means nothing elſe, thats groſſe hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy: ſuch were the Phariſees in Chriſts time, and the world is full of them; hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can we think a man in ſuch a caſe, as theſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were now in, at the point of death, would be ſo groſſe, to mock God expreſſely.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is an Hypocriſy of a finer thread, thats interpretive hypocriſy wherein we deale falſely with God and our ſelves too; ſuch as God will Judge, hypocriſy how is that, when a man reſts in ſome acts of repentance, but it failes and falls ſhort in the main, and is careleſs of that.</p>
            <p>As firſt, There are ſome actions of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, as confeſſion of ſin, calling of mercy, promiſing amendment, theſe are good, but yet more is required.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There are ſome affections and paſſions of repentance, as ſadneſſe, and ſorrow, and feare, and anxiety of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152582:44"/>mind, and other paſſionate motions, theſe all are good, but yet fall ſhort.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, What then is wanting, the main of all is that the heart muſt be changed, I ſay changed, it may be affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, dejected and troubled, and yet remain as bad as ever, ſo it is with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the terrours of God deeply affected him, ſo was <hi>Ahab</hi> ſtrangely caſt down at <hi>Elias</hi> threatnings, he was ſad in good earneſt; and what think you of <hi>Judas,</hi> was not he much affected, but no new change was wrought in their hearts, they were the ſame men ſtill, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> an oppreſſer in his heart, <hi>Ahab</hi> a perſecuter.</p>
            <p>Here then is that which makes up re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to be true and ſpirituall, and ſuch as God will accept, when it puts a new heart into us, changes our natures from what we were before, begets in us new reſolutions, that we chuſe what we refuſed, love what we hated, frames the very heart anew, in this caſe, hypocriſy works like art, ſincerity like nature, how is that; why natures works begins within, frames the inwards of a man, firſt the heart, then ſhapes the outward members,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152582:44"/>ſo doth ſincerity, but art that works upon the outſide, alters the figure, and outward lineaments goes no further, ſo doth hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy.</p>
            <p>Judge thy converſation by this tryall, art thou another man, a new frame put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, hath God taken away thy ſtony heart and given thee a heart of fleſh;</p>
            <p>A ſecond conviction of the unſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their repentance is, that it was a fleeting momentary unconſtant repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, they were not ſtedfaſt in his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, true repentance will prove laſting repentance, hypocriticall repentance is ſlippery and unconſtant.</p>
            <p>Firſt, A true convert hath an inward principle of repentance planted into him, grace is a ſecond nature, and workes conſtantly as nature doth, but an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite in his actions of reformation and repentance is moved, not by an invvard principle of God, but by ſome outward motion, when that croſſes, his converſion ſailes; the motion of piety in a good Chriſtian are like naturall motions, the motions of an hypocrite, are as artificiall motions, the motions of the Sun and of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152582:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>the clock keep time alike, and for a while we will ſay a clock goes as the Sun, I but here is a difference, the one moves out of an inward principle, naturally the other, the clock is moved by an outward prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, the weight and plummet makes it goe, and when that is down the Clock ſtands ſtill, or as in waters, the naturall ſtreame flowes alwayes, 'tis fed with a ſtreame; but a ſudden Landflood though it runs ſtrongly for a while, yet it will drye up, it hath no Spring or Fountaine to feede it.</p>
            <p>A great difference 'twixt affection that will tire, and affection that will hold out, a great difference 'twixt paſſion that is ſuddaine, comes and goes, and 'twixt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution that is conſtant, ſuddain flaſhing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of heare are one thing, and the kindly warmth at the heart is another, a good Chriſtian is the ſame out of affliction that he is in affliction, an hypocrite oh he is a new Man on his ſick bed, recover him and ye diſcover him, as covetous &amp; prophane, in affliction he vowes, in proſperity he forgets his vow, what ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 57.8. <hi>My heart is fixed, O God, my heart
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152582:45"/>is fixed: I will ſing and give praiſe. Pſal.</hi> 66.13, 14. <hi>I will pay thee my vowes, which my lips have uttered, and my mouth have ſpoken when I was in trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In repentance he hath renued his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants with God, and he will not breake with him, failings he may have, but yet he revolts not, <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution is this, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.93. <hi>I will never forget thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for by them thou haſt quickened me.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:152582:46"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke <hi>22.</hi> verſe <hi>31, 32.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And the Lord ſaid, Simon, Simon, behold, Satan hath deſired to have you, that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may ſift you as wheat: But I have pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thee, that thy faith faile not; and when thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy Brethren.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt relates to u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Saviours approach and preparation to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> death. Now this So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of righteouſneſs being to leave the Horizo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of this World, and to deſcend under the Earth, and ſit in a Cloud, he was diſmay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and affrighted, and perplexed with the expectation and feare of death; but as the Sun in a cleare evening, when it is nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſetting, caſts forth moſt beautifull and glorious beames of light; So our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152582:46"/>now approaching towards death, ſhines forth in moſt heavenly meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and exhortations to his Apoſtles. He doth that which the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded <hi>Ezechiah</hi> to do when death ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, he ſet his houſe and family in order, Like holy <hi>Jacob</hi> when he drew to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his end, he called his twelve ſons, and forewarned them of what ſhould befall them, and inſtructed them, and bleſſed them, ſo here our Saviour calls his Twelve Apoſtles, and forewarns them likewiſe of what ſhould betide them, and ſeals up his love and bleſſing to them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He makes here his laſt will and Teſtament; and publiſheth and ſeals it up to them by the inſtitution of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>verſe</hi> 19. <hi>This is the new Teſtament in my bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, He makes here a bountifull and bleſſed bequeathment to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; as <hi>Jacob</hi> to his Son <hi>Joſeph,</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathes him the portion that he had won to himſelf by his bowe and by his ſword, ſo here our Saviour bequeathes to his Diſciples, to the Church of God the great conqueſt of his own bloud, the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152582:47"/>of his death and paſſion; I bequeath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o you a Kingdom ſaith he, <hi>verſe</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Thrdly, He foretells them of troubles and afflictions, he forewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes them of temptations that ſhould befall them; he gives them notice of their grand Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that would labour to diſapoint them of their inheritance, and defeate them of the Kingdom.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Simon Simon Sathan hath deſired to winnow you as wheat,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>SO then the Text you ſee is a ſeaſonable gracious prediction of a great tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation. The hour of temptation was now falling upon the Apoſtles, and Satan was now dragging his nets and framing his pits, and ſetting his ſnares to take them. And our bleſſed Saviour not only by the Spirit of propheſie but by his alſeeing eye of divinity diſcovers all the intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Satan; and gives them notice he carries an eye on all Satans plots leaſt Satan ſhould have advantage againſt us for he is ignorant nor of his deviſes as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, he has his conſtant eye
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152582:47"/>upon his Saints and upon their enemies, his eye is upon <hi>Leviathan</hi> the old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent leaſt he ſhould annoy the Church of God. I the Lord will watch over it day and night, Hence <hi>Bernard</hi> taking into his meditation the conſtant practice of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in forewarning his Church of temptations; he terms <hi>Chriſt</hi> the creature that hath ſimpathy with man, That crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture when it ſees a man aſleep, and a Serpent or Snake making towards him to hurt him; runs to him, and ſtrikes him and awakes him that he may eſcape <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> miſchief, So here <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſees his Apoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſlumber in ſecurity, and the old Serpent making towards them to annoy them; he rouzeth them out of their ſecurity by this watch word, and tells them <hi>Simon Simon,</hi> Satan is on you and deſires to winnow you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obſerve theſe three particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, A danger foretold <hi>Simon, Simon, Satan bath deſired to winnow you as wheat,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Here is a deliverance aſſured them, but I have prayed for thee that thy faith fail not.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:152582:48"/>
               <p>Thirdly, The duty of thankfulneſſe required of them, and then when thou art converted ſtrengthen thy brethren.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, the danger foretold them there are three things obſervable in it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The perſon forewarned that is in this word, <hi>Simon, Simon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, The enemy foretold, Satan hath deſired.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The miſchiefe intended by him to winnow you as Wheat.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The Apoſtle here warned, it is ſaid here to be <hi>Peter,</hi> Chriſt directs his caveat to him, and awakens <hi>Peter</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by this quick compellation, and it carries briefly with it a threefold conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
               <p>Firſt, This compellation that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour uſeth is no men perſonate, he directs it here in a particular ſpeciall terme to him, he names him here <hi>Simon.</hi> He doth not direct his warning and caveat in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall termes, he ſaith not the Church of God is in danger, and Satan labours to bring in miſchiefe on Chriſtianity, but he brings it home to <hi>Peter</hi> in particulars, and gives the caveat to him in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152582:48"/>and it carryes a threefold intimation.</p>
               <p>Firſt, On Chriſts part, and ſo it is an intimation of ſpeciall care, he carryes a particular eye upon <hi>Peter,</hi> and upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that belongs to his care and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, he ſpeakes to him in individuall punctuall termes, he is tender of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, it argues the large and unlimited compaſſe of his knowledge, he takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of every man, he ſees our condition, he obſerves our actions, he beholds our carriage in all the turnings of our lives, his eye is on whatſoever can befall us. As it was rare and excellent in that great Commander that knew every Soldier in his Army, and could call every one by his name. I ſay it argues not onely his knowledge and inſpection, but his eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all regard and affection, he fixeth the eye of his providence upon every poor Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that belongs to him, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditates, <hi>O tu omnipotente,</hi> &amp;c. O Lord God, (ſaith he) thy care reacheth to every particular man as much, as to the whole Church, and thou as much tendreſt and art provident over every particular man, as of the whole frame of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:152582:49"/>
               <p>We are told indeed by ſome that he abſolutely intends the ſalvation of the Church in generall, he will provide that the Church of God ſhall not be ruined<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he hath built it on an impregnable Rock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but notwithſtanding they ſay that this o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that particular may, any one Chriſtian may fall away and periſh. No verily, the providence of Chriſt is as carefull for <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> and every one whoſe names are given up to him. He beares every one on his breſt and on his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as well as he ſupports the whole Church. This was foretold by <hi>David Pſalm,</hi> 72. he ſaith not onely that he will have a care that the Church ſhall flouriſh in his time, and that there ſhall be abundance of peace, but he will have a care of the pooreſt ſort, he will deliver the poor ſoule from violence, and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is every poor ſoule in his ſight: It was typified in that charge that was given up to <hi>Moſes</hi> when he tooke the charge of the Government of the people, all the people were delivered him by Pole and by tale; a muſter was made at his firſt entrance into his Government, and God
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152582:49"/>ſurveyed all the Army, a particular of them was given to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned them to God again he gives them by tale. It was typified on <hi>Aaron,</hi> he bore the names of all the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in his boſome, not onely our perſons, but our hairs, are hairs of the heads of his children, their perſons then are under his eye and obſervance, under his regard and particular inſpection. That is the firſt thing it is an intimation of particular inſpection.</p>
               <p>Secondly, This perſonall name car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries an intimation on Satans part of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, he deſires that no fleſh ſhould be ſaved, he thirſts after an univerſall deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but notwithſtanding his more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ſpight is againſt the Church of God, he takes more felicity in the ruine and overthrow of one Chriſtian then in the damnation of a 1000 others, to recover one that is gotten out of his ſnare to bring <hi>Iſrael</hi> back, after they are gotten out of <hi>Egypt</hi> it is a great joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to Satan; but above all he rejoiceth that the moſt eminent Saints, <hi>Peter</hi> and ſuch as are Pillars of the Church, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152582:50"/>of them is a great Conqueſt to him. One <hi>David</hi> is more then 10000. of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to bring him to ſin is his cheife ayme, hee hates thoſe above all. The choiceſt Saints are the marke of his greateſt malice: the image of God where it is cleareſt, enrageth Satans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice moſt. He hates us all, but thoſe that excell in vertue, and beare the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeſt Characters of God are his cheife ayme.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Above all, he feares Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and ſuch as he, if they ſtand they work great ruine to the power of Satan. <hi>Peter</hi> killed his thouſands, and <hi>Paul</hi> his 10000. If theſe ſtand they make havock of the power of Satan, and trample on principallityes and powers. Therefore as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> made it his plot to deſtroy the male Children,, ſo doth he to deſtroy the moſt maſculine Chriſtians of the higheſt improvement of grace. As it was the plot of <hi>Sampſon</hi> when he would deſtroy all the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> he goes to the Pillars and pulls them downe, ſo it is his policy above all others, he goes to <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Apoſtles, and the cheifeſt Saints, that is
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152582:50"/>the ſecond intimation of Satans malice.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, This compellation, <hi>Simon, Simon,</hi> it carryes an intimation on <hi>Peters</hi> part, that is of ſpeciall care and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection in caſe of temptation, it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to reſt in generall promiſes, the Church of God is ſure, it is built on a Rock, and there we reſt our ſelves, but we muſt make proviſion for our own ſafety. As in the caſe of War and invaſion, men are not content that the Coaſts be guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; the Caſtle fortified, &amp; that there be publick care to watch over the kingdom, but every man provides for himſelfe, and hath Armour for his owne uſe. So in the caſe of temptation, we are not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench our ſelves with generall promiſes of the Church that is built on a Rock, and it ſhall ſtand, and the power of Hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it. It is true Satan in his War againſt the Church will looſe the maine battell, and he and his inſtruments that fight in a damned quarrell, they ſhall be overthrown. O but if thou look not to thy ſelfe, thou mayeſt have a wound and be taken in the battell.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:152582:51"/>
               <p>See this care of perſonall proviſion how <hi>Paul</hi> urgeth it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Brethre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> if any be overtaken by infirmities, you that are ſpirituall reſtore ſuch an one with the ſpirit of meekneſſe, conſidering thy ſelf leaſt thou be tempted.</hi> In the exhortation, firſt he begins in the Plurall, Brethren, you that are ſpirituall recover you ſuch a one; but when he comes to caution conſider thy ſelf. A man would think it were ſolleciſme, and indeed it ſeems to be a ſlip in Grammer; Brethren, look to thy ſelf, and you that are ſpirituall ſee that thou be not tempted. No, it is an elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for in compaſſion all muſt come in, but in cantion every man muſt look to himſelf; Brethren help one another, but let every one look to himſelf in caſe of temptation: conſider thy ſelf leaſt thou be tempted. Thus we ſee the firſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, it is a name of perſonall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, <hi>Simon Simon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, This compellation it is a name more naturall to him then his other name; he calls him not <hi>Cephas</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and by theſe names after he uſeth to call him, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> paſſeth by theſe, and calls
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152582:51"/>him by the name he brought with him before he was a Diſciple; <hi>Simon</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now in the caſe of temptation he doth not mind him of his priviledge; thou art <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rock, thou art a ſtone, and theſe ſhall ſecure thee and the divine promiſes; but confider what thou art in thy ſelf a weak man diveſted of all priviledge &amp; ſecurity by thy own naturall condition, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about with many infirmities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In caſe of temptation the ſafeſt way is not to conſider our ſtrength but our weakneſſe.</head>
               <p>NOt what we are by priviledges that comes from without us; but what we are in our own weakneſſe, if we be left to our ſelves. As the Lord ſpeaks in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he tells them of their danger, he calls them, thou <hi>Worm Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob;</hi> he puts them not in mind of their excellencies and prerogatives, but what they were in themſelves, poor Worms, unable to reſcue themſelves or to reſiſt any force. The beſt way is to conſider what we are in our weakneſſe, and not in our ſtrength; Thoughts of ſtrength breed ſecurity, and are forerunners of ruine;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152582:52"/>but thoughts of weakneſs &amp; inſufficiency awaken diligence to prevent our danger; ſtill we ſee in all the ſupplies and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments that the Saints had, they ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beſt that were conſcientious of their weakneſſe: What furniſhed <hi>Moſes</hi> and made him ſo compleate a man for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but the urging of his own weakneſſe. Firſt he pleades his own weakneſſe, Lord I cannot ſpeak, God ſupplies that; And then another, I am fearfull, and he argues many inſufficiencies of himſelf, and the pleading of his inſufficiencies gained him abundance of ſtrength from God: in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation remember the beſt of us, as the ſpirit is willing, ſo the fleſh is weak: And conſider not onely that we are built on a Rock, but our old foundation in the duſt; not to remember that we are <hi>Peters</hi> and <hi>Ceph's,</hi> and are ſtrengthned by privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, but <hi>Simon, Simon</hi> compaſſed with infirmities. That is the ſecond, it is a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall name.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, This compellation it is a name ingeminated, our Saviour is not content once to jogg and awaken him out of his drowzineſs, &amp; infirmities, but he doubles it
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152582:52"/>and quickens him up with a vehement compellation, and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, There is ſome quickning ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this ingemination, <hi>Simon Simon,</hi> a little before the Apoſtles were fallen into a ſtrange diſpute; and debate among themſelves who ſhould be the greateſt, they were at a great diſpute, they would needs know who ſhould be the ſupreme, they imagined a kind of Popery, who ſhould be the leader of all the reſt; our Saviour ſees it and pitches it, and calls them off with ſharpnes and acrimony: are you thus diſputing for Maſterſhip and ſpremacy; the common enemy is upon you, Satan is at hand ready to ſwallow you up, and you are together by the ears.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>It is the uſual condition of the Church of God, when they are in the greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute and objecting one againſt another for ſupremacy, and Maſterſhip they are in the greateſt danger, the greater ſeverity is on them.</head>
               <p>Thus <hi>Jeremiah</hi> takes of the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of poor <hi>Baruch,</hi> The Lord will
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152582:53"/>bring a captivity upon the land, and ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou great things for thy ſelf; The common enemy is upon us, and hath caſt in his fire balls of contention, and ſhall we contend who ſhall be Miſtris, it is a ſecret check, he ſhews, that while they were diſputing about ſupremacy they were in danger, while they think they ſtand in the height, they fall down as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſaith.</p>
               <p>Secondly, This ingemination that our Saviour uſeth; it carries with it a great ſtrength of warmth and heat of affection, he looks on their danger, he pitties their ſecurity and tenders their welfare, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is ſtirred in all tenderneſſe of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; to bring them out of the ſnare? O <hi>Simon Simon;</hi> It is the gracious love of our Saviour, he hath not onely an eye of inſpection on our danger, but his bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els are ſtirred with compaſſion; they are rolled together, his heart melts in our afflictions and temptation.</p>
               <p>This form of ſpeaking is uſed in any extremity of the Church: In their ſorrow in captivity, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. See how God ſpeaks, I have ſeen, I have ſeen; In the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152582:53"/>danger of <hi>Iſaac</hi> to be ſlain by <hi>Abraham,</hi> God poſts an Angell out of heaven, and the meſſenger comes upon the wings of the wind; and ſaith <hi>Abraham Abraham, &amp;c.</hi> So in the caſe of deſolation and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that the Church was in, how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably God ſpeaks to his people; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ye, comfort ye my people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There is no tender hearted Mother, that ſprings forth into paſſion and tenderneſſe of affection, upon ſight of the danger of her child, as God is ſtirred to compaſſion, and his bowels yearn to catch us as fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand out of the fire, to deliver us out of the ſnare of Satan.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It is a quick ſpeech <hi>Simon Simon,</hi> to awaken and ſtirr them out of their greateſt ſecurity. The Apoſtles were at leiſure to fall into many diſputes, and never conſidered the danger of them; <hi>Chriſt</hi> is fain to double his voice, and to lift it up as a Trumpet to awaken them, As a man that ſees fire break out of his neighbours houſe; and knows that they are all aſleep, he bounceth and knocks at the door, and calls to awaken them out of danger: ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> is vehement and impotu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152582:54"/>There is a kind of Lethargy that falls on Chriſtians ſometimes that they muſt be affrighted out off by fearfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellations: The beſt of Gods Saints have need of theſe warning pieces to be ſhot off at their ears, not only the wicked that lye benumed in ſecurity, and are taken by Satan at his pleaſure in every tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but the beſt of Gods children. And our ſpirituall dangers do no more affect us, then the bodily danger of <hi>Lot</hi> when he was loath to eſcape, and it ſeemed a fable to his ſons when they were told of it, therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> is earneſt and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate with them; ſo you ſee the firſt thing the perſon warned <hi>Simon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond is the enemy foretold, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan deſires to winnow you; And here are theſe two particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The enemy himſelf that is Satan.</p>
               <p>Then ſecondly, the proviſion and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration he was to do this miſchief, he did earneſtly deſire.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Here is our enemie Satan, it is one of the names, that the Scripture deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers the enemy of our ſalvation by, ſome times he is called Diabolus the Accuſer
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152582:54"/>ſomtimes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Tempter, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Apollyon a deſtroyer, here Satan an enemy, and it is a great aggravation of the danger to know the greatneſſe of the enemy that beſets us, he is Satan.</p>
               <p>Firſt, A malitious deadly enemy, he hunts for the precious ſoules of men.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He is a ſubtle crafty enemy he knows, as <hi>John</hi> ſpeakes, he hath the miſtery and depth of temptation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, He is an old inveterate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced enemy, he is beaten to this trade, he is excetciſed and verſed in the art of temptation. See the danger of this ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my by three reaches and depths of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife that he conveyes in his temptation.</p>
               <p>Firſt, This temptation that he ſets on <hi>Peter</hi> by, it was an importunate tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there was great importunity in this temptation to ſet on <hi>Peter</hi> and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. There were many diſcouragements that might have deter'd him from ſetting on the Apoſtles, the Apoſtles were not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed, they lay not naked, they were not as a Citty whoſe wals were broken down, open to invaſion, but there were many things conſiderable in the Apoſtles that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152582:55"/>might have driven him off from his temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and yet he would aſſault them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, They were in Chriſts ſociety, a great priviledge, and it was a great diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to Satan to ſet on Chriſts ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, thoſe that lived and were in the ſanctuary of his ſociety. If Satan had ſet upon ſtrangers, thoſe that were out of Chriſts love, as a bird from the neſt. So is a man that ſtrayes from his places ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> a man that is out of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Chriſt and of good men, he lies open to every free booter, Satan may take him at his pleaſure, if Satan take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> man at a Stage-Play, he ſeizeth upon him on his own ground, but the Apoſtles were in the Sanctuary of Chriſts ſociety; ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Satan dares break into Chriſts family, and offer temptations and aſſaults upon his own ſervants about his body; no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, not the whole Church of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſociety and preſence of Chriſt ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deter Satan from aſſaulting by tempta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo it was in <hi>Judas,</hi> he wonne hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from his Maſters company, he rook hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from his heeles, and carryed him away b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> temptation, as it were in ſpight of Chriſt
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152582:55"/>that was the firſt determent they were in, Chriſts company and family, yet Satan ſets on them.</p>
               <p>A ſecond, diſcouragement that might have kept him from tempting the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, they were in the ſtate of grace in a bleſſed condition, they were regenerate. Having ſanctifying grace, it ſtrengthens us againſt temptations. Grace in the heart of men is as a Garriſon that God hath ſet to keep us from Satan, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeakes, ye are kept by faith to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. The word ſignifies ſo to keep, as a Caſtle is kept by a Garriſon. God ſets a ſtrong Garriſon in the heart of a Chriſtian, faith and grace beates off Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans aſſaults, notwithſtanding the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of grace in the hearts and minds of theſe Apoſtles, it diſcourageth not Satan, but he ſets on them. The holieſt man, the greateſt Saint, nay Chriſt himſelfe, Satan dares aſſault by temptation, as <hi>Gregory</hi> on that place of <hi>Job</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Leviathan,</hi> he drinkes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p whole Rivers, the wicked of the world, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay he thinks to drink up <hi>Jordan,</hi> the Church of God, he will try if he can
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152582:56"/>ſwallow the Saints, nothing can diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him, no, not grace in the regenerate.</p>
               <p>A third determent that might have kept him, and yet he is importunate, they were ſupported with the but reſſe and ſtrength of promiſes, they had ſpeciall aſſurance that they ſhould not fall; None that are committed to him, Father I have kept them all ſaith Chriſt, and they ſhall not periſh, yet Satan in deſpight of all Gods promiſes wraſtles with his Children, and will ſee if he can beguile them, as it was with him, he diſputed Gods truth, hath God ſaid ye ſhall dye. No, ſo he diſputes, with a faith of a Chriſtian, hath God promiſed that you ſhall not faile, hath he aſſured you of your perſeverance, no ſuch matter, it is falſe doctrine, he will aſſure us, there is no ſuch ground and priviledge, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpell, are no diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Here was a new ſupply of grace that might have diſcouraged him, they had been even now at the Sacrament, firſt the Sacrament of the Paſſeover, there was the blood of the Lamb ſprinkled o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:152582:56"/>them to keep them from the deſtroying Angell, yet he durſt ſet on them, and then the Sacrament of the Lords ſupper, that great conduit pipe of grace, they had receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed new ſtrength from Chriſt, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all theſe advantages that the Apoſtles had, the malice of Satan is thus great, and his opportunity, that he ſets on them.</p>
               <p>In what caſe are they that neither live in the ſociety of Chriſt, but in the walk and range of Satan, that have not the leaſt part of grace, that have no hold upon the promiſes, that have not any ſtrength from the word and Sacraments. If he doth thus upon the green Trees, <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt, what will become of the dry ones, thoſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t are deſtitute of all theſe privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. That is the firſt conſideration, the danger of this enemy of his importunities.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, Is the conſideration of this temptation and the danger of it, that Satan ſets upon them, we find it was a humane temptation, the temptation that <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles were aſſaulted? with what was it no diabolicall ſuggeſtion but ſave thy ſelfe, preſerve thy ſelfe from danger, provide for thine own
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152582:57"/>run not into needleſſe trouble, thou canſt doe no good, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaith, it was a meere naturall incentive, it was not dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bollicall. Our own courſe dictates this, eſcape danger, goe not into needleſſe trouble, he bids him not curſe Chriſt and Blaſpheme, and ſpeake horribly of him; but he comes with a temptation of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall affection. Here is a ſecond cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reach of Satan. We are not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at him; but when he appeares in his own ſhape, as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes, when he comes with horrible Blaſphemies. O but he folds up himſelfe in our bowels, and hedges his temptations in our own naturall affections, he bids the Apoſtle, thou ſhalt provide againſt danger, be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure againſt trouble, and this is the moſt dangerous temptation when he works with our ſelves, and ſhoots our owne ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes in our own faces; as the Axe bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes the helve of the wood by which it is cut downe after, ſo, Satan borrowes temptations from our affections, he goes on in our owne temper of nature and diſpoſition, he bids us love our lives and provide for our ſelves, but they are hiſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152582:57"/>Serpents, thoſe temptations are moſt dangerous and deadly that come under a humane notion. This is the ſecond.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Yet it was a temptation of an Adverſary, a man would think it were a very freindly temptation, provide for thy ſelfe, eſcape danger. If Satan ſhould come with a horrid temptation, deſtroy thy ſelfe, make thy ſelfe away, ruſh on danger, theſe are horrible; but he comes in the hearts of a freind, and tells him he may doe a great deale of miſcheife to himſelfe, and incurre the diſpleaſure of the high Preiſt, and looſe his friends, and hazard his eſtate, and run into danger without advantange. This is the voyce certainly of a friend, but this was the voyce of an Adverſary. The moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous temptations are thoſe that come under the ſemblance and appearance of good will and councell. We can ſtart back when one bids us ruſh into miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife, and caſt our ſelves downe, but to ſave our lives and provide for our profit, to take care of our familyes, to inrich our ſelves for hereafter, to provide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hard times. O we thank every
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152582:58"/>man for theſe councells, he is a good freind, yet notwithſtanding Satan maskes himſelfe in this habit above all other. A falſe freind is the worſt foe; as thoſe <hi>Pyrats</hi> are moſt dangerous that hangs out falſe colours, that pretend league and yet ſet on us, we are afraid of Satan when he comes in his own appearance, but when he comes like <hi>Samuel</hi> in the Prophets mantle, when he comes to Chriſt in the ſhape of <hi>Peter,</hi> when he comes in the perſwaſion of a wife in the neceſſityes of Children, in the councell of freinds; yet we ſhould diſcerne theſe to be the temptations of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, thus you ſee the firſt thing the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that tempts, it is Satan.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is the nature of the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, he hath deſired, that hath two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Here is the great bent of his will, and then the reſtraint of his power.</p>
               <p>The bent of his will, he earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to bring temptation, but he muſt deſire it. But if you would know the ſuſpenſion of his power, he is not able to doe that which he moſt deſires, he is
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152582:58"/>bounded and limitted; he longs for it, and he muſt deſire it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Here is the great earneſt deſire of Satan to aſſault by temptation, and to bring us to ſin, Take his deſire in theſe three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, See, it is the very bent and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his nature to do miſchief, his deſire is not for deſire to do good for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but onely for ill to us, he longs not for his own ſalvation, but for our perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; As it is naturall for Lyons to be cruell, and for Serpents to be venemous; ſo it is the nature of Satan to do miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, malice ſeeks not its own good; but to do others hurt; you may know Satan by his ymps, &amp; the old one by his whelps, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> a wicked man deſires to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o miſchief, it is death to Satan not to do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, See his deſire further, in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o do miſchief in his dayly malicious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſations, it is that term of infamy that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Scripture puts on him; he is the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſer of the brethren, that accuſeth before God day night, the great Informer againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Church. There is no ſin paſſeth by
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152582:59"/>us, but he ſcores it up; did not I ſee this, and this hath not ſuch a Saint committed ſuch a ſin? He is the great <hi>Doeg</hi> of the Church, as <hi>David</hi> curſeth <hi>Doeg</hi> for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and it is <hi>Auſtins</hi> obſervation and direction for us on thoſe Pſalms, when we ſing thoſe Pſalms where <hi>David</hi> curſeth <hi>Doeg</hi> &amp; thoſe that accuſed him to <hi>Saul;</hi> we ſhould turn from the little <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egs</hi> of the world, to the great <hi>Doeg</hi> of the Church, Satan that accuſeth them day and night, and thirſts after their deſtruction, and weaves cunning accuſations againſt the Church of God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, This great deſire of our ill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the earneſt importunity, he uſeth to God himſelf that we may be given over to him. He prayes not for his own pardon but for damnation, he prayes not tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf, may go to Heaven, but that we may go to Hell; he makes no prayer to God, but againſt the Church no petition but to ill. See how ready he was to ſeduce <hi>Ahab,</hi> here am I, he proffers his ſervice he deſires imployment to work miſchief how ſubmiſſively he deſires that he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> winnow <hi>Peter,</hi> how he ſollicites <hi>Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:152582:59"/>that he would not caſt him out, but that he would ſuffer him ſtill to torment the bodies of Gods people. It is ſtrange, he is a proud ſpirit, and pride diſdains to ſtoup, but his malice over-rules his pride, and he falls on his knees, and ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites, and begs, and importunes God that he may have ſo much leave as to do miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</p>
               <p>Then as you ſee the bent of his will, ſo in the ſecond place, if he deſires it, here is a ſecond thing obſervable, the ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his power, he is reſtrained and chained up, he hath a clog upon him, a limitation, to fall a begging, he is fain to deſire it, without leave he can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>Firſt, He hath an Originall prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he is caſt out of all power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he is the baſeſt of all Gods creatures, he hath no power over the meaneſt, he can do nothing to <hi>Job</hi> but by permiſſion. But you will ſay <hi>Job</hi> was an holy man; He could do nothing to <hi>Ahab</hi> but by Gods allowance, nay he had not power over the Swine without he begg <hi>Chriſts</hi> leave. Its <hi>Tertullians</hi> Meditation, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152582:60"/>not hurt a hair of our heads (ſaith he) nay even the very hairs and briſtles of the Swine, he hath not power over them, he muſt beg leave of God to enter into the heard of Swine, his reſtraint is ſuch.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If ever God allow him, in all his permiſſions God manageth them with his wiſe diſpenſation, he cannot do what he would, but what God gives him leave, God alwayes carries a power over him, he holds the end of the chaine in his hand. In the tryall of <hi>Job</hi> he could do nothing while he had leave given him, God ſlips one linke of the chaine, he lets him trye what he would do, he doth that to the utmoſt &amp; then he ſtops; God gives him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother linke of the chaine, but there he ſtops. It is that, that gives us great ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he carries him in ſuch a ſort as that he can take him off, he limits him, and ſets him bounds of moderation, he hath great ſtrength of malice, great deſire, great cunning but his power is limitted, he walks as a Thief with his keeper, he is a dangerous Thief, but the keeper walks with him, and he hath ſhackells on his heels. This is the ſecond thing.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:152582:60"/>
               <p>I come to the laſt, the miſchief intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Winnow you as wheat,</hi> Now this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Winnowing</hi> it is an ordinary fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar action conceivable by any, and this repreſents unto us the nature of Satans temptation, and that in theſe three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Winnowing</hi> or fifting it is no acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſtrength, of force and violence, but of skill and cunning and dexterity. He that comes to purge corn by <hi>Winnowing,</hi> he pours not all out, he uſeth no violent action on it, but by ſlight of hand as it were a cunning dexterity and art that he hath, he uſeth this action that we call <hi>Winnowing</hi> ſo all the temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan they are actions of cunning not of power, he may perſwade and ſeduce us by the dexterity of his skill by inveigling us by temptations, but he cannot force and compell us ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi> he hath a great deal of power, and ſtrength and cunning, he may circumvent us but he cannot powerfully overthrow us. It is not in the power of Satan to force the will of any to yield to his temptations. It is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in the firſt temptation, he aſſumed
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152582:61"/>the body of the Serpent a ſubtile crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not of a Lyon; a creature of force he cannot break in upon us by force, he cannot open the door and come in upon thee, if thou open not thy own heart. It is onely God that hath power immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, to enter into the ſoul, he onely that hath omnipotency, can frame and work and bend the will according to his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; Satan can follicite and tempt us, and perſwade us, he cannot overpower us, he can onely over-reach us, he cannot ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh thy ſoul, he may inveigle it. If thou reſiſt and beat him back; The will of any man is impregnable to Satan, it is onely in the power of God to work on the ſoul; it is onely an art or ſlight that Satan hath, he is an intreater, and ſeducer, not an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrower, That is the firſt, it is a meer trick of exterity and skill.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Winnowing</hi> it is not one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or action and there is an end, it is not preſently done, but oft and oft, it is a frequent action an agitation rather, He that comes to <hi>Winnow</hi> corn he uſeth not one motion and then ceaſeth, but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peates and renews it, he exerciſeth the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152582:61"/>ſame action again and again; So it is with Satans temptations, it is not one ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, that he is content with, and if you deny that he is gone, yet he knocks at the door again, he is importunate, he will take no denyal, but ſollicites and renews his onſets and compaſſeth us about afreſh: it is his continuall courſe as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, it is the buffeting of Satan, Satans buffets are blows and blows; a ſecond and a third blow over and over. This is the courſe of Satan, he will not be beaten once and then leave, but he will come the ſecond and the third time, and he then leaves but for a ſeaſon, &amp; after renews all his forces.</p>
               <p>Firſt, We know his malice is infinite and reſtles, he can never give over doing hurt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Satan knows not what tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation will proſper and ſucceed; he knows not truely and infallibly the ground of our hearts, when one tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore failes, he will trye another, and another. He goes to <hi>Job</hi> and tryes him in his goods, it may be thoſe will vex him, and then in his children, it may be a tender father may be overcome, but
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152582:62"/>
                  <hi>Job</hi> overcame him, then he tryes him with a ſhrewd wife, and then with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull friends, he knows not the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the heart.</p>
               <p>And then he knows that we are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in a temper, ſometime we are more watchfull, ſometime more drowſie, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſets upon us at all ſeaſons.</p>
               <p>Laſtly he knows that importunity will weary and tyre a man; that thoſe that will not yeild out of love, will out of vexation give an anſwer to be quit, Thus Satan he makes his <hi>Winnowing</hi> a frequent act.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Winnowing</hi> is an action of great ſtirring &amp; motion, a combuſtion and beating together, there is a great ſtirring and beating together in temptation: Satan brings no temptation that falls upon the ſoul of a Chriſtian like this, to be under the buffetings and <hi>winnowings</hi> and aſſaults of Satan. It puts the whole of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an mans heart to it, it makes him weary, <hi>I go mourning all the day long ſaith</hi> David; It makes the Saints of God dejected in ſpirit, weary in ſoul, that Satan will never let them reſt, but ſets on them with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152582:62"/>buffetings, fightings without, and fears within; temptations on all ſides, It makes them loath themſelves that Satan ſhould ſee ſo much evill in them, as to think to draw them to ſuch ſins by ſuch tempations. As <hi>Gregory</hi> mourned when he was advanced to the <hi>Papacy</hi> ſaith he, Lord I ſee that the world ſees ſome ill in mee, I am not Crucified to the world as I ſhould. As a chaſt ſpirit is grieved that the Devill ſhould think him ſuch a one as would yield to the temptation of uncleannes, It makes them mourn, there is no bitterneſſe to this, to be under the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation of Satan, to be alway in the ſive and in the fanne, alway to have the flayle, and to be buffeted with tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Winnowing it is an action, that diſcernes and tryes, a man ſees a heape of Corn lye on the floore, but he knows not which is good, and which is light Corne; ſo promiſcuouſly when we live all at eaſe and peace, and ſettle on our dreggs, we know not who are ſound Chriſtians, but come to the winde and to the fanne, come to the tryall and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152582:63"/>ſee what temptations will do, you ſhall ſee which is weighty and full corn then; and which is chaff and duſt and light corn, ſo temptations ſhews a man to himſelf, it makes known who are probata, and who are not, who are reprobate corn and duſt &amp; chaff in the Church, &amp; who are good grain and weighty Corn; ſaith <hi>Jerom</hi> a man is to be thought to be ſuch a one as he approves himſelf to be in the Whirlwind of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Canſt thou indure afflictions and not murmure? canſt thou grapple with Satan, and his temptations, and not yeild? O ſaith <hi>James,</hi> we account them bleſſed that undergoe temptations. It will ſhew thee to thy ſelfe, it will make thee know whether thou be an empty husky Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, or whether there be good corn in thee; It is a matter of tryall.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all this winnowing is a purging action, it is vexatious, but it is alwayes profitable, it purgeth out ſome corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereſoever there is winnowing. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Satan intends all for deſtruction but the live is Gods, though Satan uſe it, and the Church of God is alway the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the purer the more it is purged
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152582:63"/>from all droſſe, by theſe temptations. What doth Satan get by all the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and afflictions? by all the ſtirs that he raiſeth in the Church of God? He purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Church, he cleanſeth it, he makes it pure, he purgeth the droſs from it.</p>
               <p>The Corn before it is winnowed it is bigger, it is more in bulke, but after it is winnowed it is purer in ſubſtance. The Oare before it is caſt into the fyning Pot it is a bigger maſſe, but after it is purer in mettall, ſo the Church of God in all theſe tryalls of falſe doctrines and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations what ever comes to try the Church, there is falling away, and men are gone, to faction and carryed away to ſedition and fractions; but all our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, it is but the light duſt and chaffe that is blowne away with the wind, the good Corn remaines. In all Satans get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all his gain is nothing but a heape of chaffe, not one true Chriſtian at the heart is drawn away, as it is <hi>Amos,</hi> 9. Not one graine of corne ſhall fall to the earth, all that Satan gains by all the troubles in the Chriſtian world, by all his falſe doctrines who are they? They are ſet down in the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:152582:64"/>Revelations, they are ſuch as there names are not written in the book of life. As it was in the war between the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> &amp; the <hi>Midianites,</hi> all the <hi>Midianites</hi> were ſlain, and not one of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo in all the temptations and aſſaults that the Church ſuffers, not one Saint pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth, not one graine of Corne miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carryes, the gaine that Satan hath, is the light Chaffe, all that fall away by theſe ſeductions are but the looſe haires that fall off from the head of the Church in that ſickneſſe. Thus you ſee the third thing; the miſcheife intended, it is the winnowing. So much for this time.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:152582:64"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LUKE 11.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>If ye then, being evil; know how to give good gifts unto your Children; how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the holy Spirit to them that ask him?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we caſt back our eyes to to the former Verſes, we ſhall find in the Context a Gracious Encouragement of Chriſt to his Diſciples, and in them to the whole Church, to quicken them to the exerciſe of Prayer, for the unfolding their wants to the throne of Grace. Were we well acquainted with the nature of this duty of Invocation; or, did we conſider the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of this duty; it's the Lock and Key of Heaven, it opens the Store-houſe of the Mercies of God; it's the Bucket that draws up the Water of Salvation. Or,</p>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:152582:65"/>
            <p>Secondly, Did we conſider the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it puts upon us, it ſets us in a degree into the preſence of God, gives acceſs to his preſence; it maintains continual inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe between Heaven and us. Or,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Did we conſider the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts that ariſe from it; it mitigates Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, compoſeth Diſtractions, it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts in Diſtreſſes; and what not? Were theſe things well conſidered, a man would think we ſhould have little reaſon to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force this Duty.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, in the Neglect of this; Did we conſider the alienation of our Souls from God. Or,</p>
            <p>Secondly, our own guiltineſs, that makes us ſhie to come into his preſence; the dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our hearts to any ſpiritual ſervice, and with what wearineſs we ſerve the Lord. Or,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that we think well of our own Infidelity, which makes us conceive there is no profit in our prayers; that makes us ſay in our hearts, all our prayers vaniſh in the air.</p>
            <p>Theſe things well conſidered, Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement is neceſſary.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:152582:65"/>
            <p>In the ſecond Verſe he firſt preſcribes a form of Prayer, frames our ſupplications for us: <hi>We know not how to pray as we ought.</hi> He himſelf draws our petitions. Did a King draw a Petition to be put up to himſelf, it would be a hopeful ſigne of a Grant. He teacheth not onely what to pray, but he preſcribes a manner how to pray, ſo to offer up out Suits that they may be ſucceſsful. If we fail in the manner, we may return empty, it will not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable; they muſt be fervent, conſtant, and confident, and ſo our Saviour teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>It's a great Encouragement, that he invites, perſwades, exhorts to abound in prayer. Be of good comfort; he calls us, perſwades us to come. S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, Doſt thou think that he will deny thee that calls thee? Nay, he ſues to thee to come: And then, the main En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of all, is the gracious aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he gives to us; <hi>Thy prayers</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall be accepted,</hi> granted and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. God takes it in good part, <hi>he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth not the prayer of the poor,</hi> but gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly accepts of it: And,</p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:152582:66"/>
            <p>Secondly, hee yeelds, grants, and ſubſcribes to our petitions, anſwers all our deſires; he puts us not off with a bare acceptance, but fulfils and grants.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he not onely accepts, fulfils, and grants, but rewards and gives all that we ask; nay, he gives more than we ask, becauſe we are ſubject to ask amiſs; he doth not only regard us, but relieves us and rewards us.</p>
            <p>So the words, they are a gracions aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that Chriſt gives to the Church, that they ſhould not only be heard, but ſpeed in all their prayers: and not by way of hopeful inſinuation: a bare inſinuation, as that in <hi>Zephaniah</hi> Chap. 2. v. 3. <hi>Seek ye the Lord, all ye meek of the Earth, which have wrought his Judgement,</hi> &amp;c. It may be ye ſhall be hid in the deep of the Lords Anger. Or like that inſinuation of the Prophet <hi>Joel. Who knowes if God will be merciful unto us.</hi> — No 'tis more, 'tis not onely a bare promiſe that we ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, but an aſſurance that our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall be granted; and Faith, when it meets with a promiſe, it works wonders: Yet there is more, our Saviour aſſures it,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152582:66"/>and proves it by force of Arguments and Demonſtrations, he contends and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes with our infidelity. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, Lord, I am aſſured of it, becauſe thou ſayeſt it: But how much more when Chriſt proves it by argumen s; <hi>Speak but the word Lord,</hi> and Faith will reſt upon it; but when arguments and reaſons are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, what Faith can denye? Chriſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, proves, and confirms it to us. Oh happy men that we are! that for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment and confirmation of our Faith, Chriſt will argue, diſpute, and ſtrive with our Infidelity; and what wretches are we if we do not yield. See how his arguments are framed, by way of a double ſimilitude.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from the ſimilitude of a friend, there's hope. <hi>Which of you having a friend,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 5. Kind importunity admits no denyal. <hi>I have made you my friends,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to his Diſciples. This is a ſtrong argument, and yet a doubting Faith ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that friendſhip may be broke, love may grow cold; I, but Chriſt argues from the ſimilitude of a Father, friends may prove unkind, yet a Father will not grow unnatural to his Childe. God is our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152582:67"/>O the bowells of a loving Father, that's far beyond the boſome of a friend! What can Infidelity object againſt this? Obſerve in this diſcourſe three particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the proof of the Argument, ſet down in the ſimilitude; <hi>If ye then being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, know how to give good gifts unto your Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the Concluſion, drawn from the Argument; <hi>Shall give the holy Spirit to them that ask him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Illation or ſtrength of the Argument, <hi>how much more ſhall your &amp;c.</hi> So there are three things to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the propoſition of the Similitude.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Concluſion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the proportion, how it holds, <hi>how much more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let's come to the Similitude it ſelf, and conſider, firſt the matter of it, ſecondly the uſe that Chriſt makes of this Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
            <p>The Similitude it ſelf lies upon theſe words: <hi>Ye that are evill men know how to give good gifts unto your Children.</hi> Here are three truths ſuppoſed by our Saviour.</p>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:152582:67"/>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Ye,</hi> all the ſort of you, this is your ſtate and condition, <hi>Ye are evill and ſinful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is this, <hi>Ye</hi> that are evill, have ſome principals of good in you, ſome truths remain in you; you know how to doe ſome things right and good.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, you that are evill and ſinfull have this principle preſerv'd in you, you know how to give good gifts to your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, how to love and ſeek the welfare and good of your Children.</p>
            <p>Firſt, you that are evill and ſinfull. This Tincture of evill, Chriſt objects againſt them. It points not at the moſt godleſs profaneſt ſinners, ſinners of the firſt mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude; as murthering <hi>Cain,</hi> traitorous <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> wicked <hi>Abſolom;</hi> we yield theſe to be wicked men, and yet this title reacheth to them alſo, they are not free from this imputation. But further, the men that Chriſt ſpeaks too here, they are his own Diſciples, ſuch as put themſelves under his Doctrine and Diſcipline; nay more, they were men regenerate, ſuch as might call God Father, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, ſuch as God accounts and ownes to be his owne Children, and they owne him their Father;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152582:68"/>nay more, men that had made a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in Religion, men given to Devotion and Prayer; <hi>Lord teach us how to pray.</hi> Notwithſtanding their dignity of Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the priviledge of their Son-ſhip, their piety and devotion, Chriſt tells them they are evill and ſinfull; this ſhould put all, even the very beſt, to bluſh, and cry out with the Leper in the Law, <hi>I am unclean, I am unclean.</hi> We are all unclean, it ſhould make us take up <hi>John</hi>'s confeſſion, <hi>If we ſay that we have no ſin, there is no truth in us;</hi> this is not only a ſtrain of humility, but a true confeſſion of verity, <hi>we are all ſinners.</hi> But, how far may theſe men be ſaid to be evill men and ſinners?</p>
            <p>Firſt, it was not by their natural eſtate and condition, that they were evil, as the <hi>Manichees</hi> unfold this Text; for God made all good, and very good, we came unſpotted out of his hands; alſo, Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſin was much abated in them, and new principles of grace infuſed, ſo they could not be ſaid to be wicked men; he accepts his for Saints, and they are waſhed, and cleanſed in his ſight; then, how far may the Saints of God be ſaid to be evil men?</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:152582:68"/>
            <p>Firſt, the beſt and holieſt men may be ſaid to be evil, and wicked; as in the very beſt of men are the reliques of much foul Corruption, which makes them evil and ſinful: Original ſin, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly pardoned, yet imperfectly purged; purg'd from the death of ſin, but not from the diſeaſe; the beſt of us all have the ſwadling Clouts of our firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, in which we were wrapt; the defilements of original ſin, ſtick cloſe by <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall: We were not caſt onely into a puddle of mire, but upon a heap of ſtones, having ſo bruiſed us, that this is ſubject to the very beſt of us to be ſtyl'd evil and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the beſt of Gods Saints, are lyable to this imputation of <hi>evil,</hi> and <hi>ſinfull;</hi> the good that's wrought in us, by regeneration, is ſo weak and feeble, by our Corruption; the Conflicts that the grace of God finds in us, makes all the graces of God imperfect, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith of Civil war. There are thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary principles in us, that the beſt of us are liable to this imputation, as <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id</hi> ſaith, <hi>O Lord thine eyes, ſee thee feeble im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152582:69"/>of grace,</hi> thy eyes behold the weak beginnings of grace, <hi>thy eye-lids try the Children of men:</hi> not when he looks with the eye of Juſtice, but with the eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids of his Mercy; whereby he connives and winks at us, that he may find us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable; the beſt of all Gods Saints have thoſe imperfections, that makes them cry out, We are evil and ſinful.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are evil and ſinful; our Saviour puts them in Compare with God; the very beſt of Gods Saints are nothing but Corruption; if we have ſanctification, it is by participation from him; the ſtars with-draw their light, when his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry appears, the view of which, made the Saints of God to tremble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Woe unto me</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah) I am undone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>I have ſeen the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you have the firſt truth verified. —<hi>Ye are evil and ſinful.</hi> I come now to the ſecond; though by nature ye are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and evil, and tainted with Corruption, yet there are ſome impreſſions of equity, ſome principles of common honeſty ſtill preſerved; not onely thoſe that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:152582:69"/>but thoſe that are totally evil; thoſe that are unſanctified, have ſome rules of honeſty engraven upon them, ſome impreſſions of the image of God, that image not wholly defaced, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning truths and rules of morality, which nature hath ſtill preſerved. Nature it ſelf ſtarts back at ſome abominations in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate man, the Conſcience of an unregenerate man, checks it ſelf at ſome horrible impiety. In a ſpiritual ſenſe, all moral vertues are but vices; as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaith, all ſacred truths are not to be known, but by revelation, natural en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments are beneficial, as one benefit of the remainder of nature is, that they which croſs not the rules of morality live more innocent; For, were it not that thoſe principles bare ſway in moſt mens lives, common honeſty and juſtice could not be maintained.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by nature we can never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to grace, and ſo by thoſe vertues we cannot prevail with God for Salvation; Yet they may for a temporal reward, as in the <hi>Romans,</hi> God rewarded moral ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue with victory and proſperity.</p>
            <pb n="140" facs="tcp:152582:70"/>
            <p>The third benefit it gets, they that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the rules of nature, their accompt at the laſt day ſhall be far more eaſie; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the Heathen ſhall be all turned into Hell, but the Damnation ſhall be more eaſie; <hi>Socrates</hi> leſſe puniſh'd than <hi>Cato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, a man that lives according to the rules of nature, keeps within the compaſs of theſe principles; though not able to reach at Salvation, yet their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion is more eaſie; it's more poſſible to gain him to grace, this ſtock of nature is fit to graff grace and religion on more kindly; yet at the beſt it cannot fructifie, and bring forth fruit to eternal life, but grace being graffed, it will fructifie to Salvation. A man within the ſphere of morality, that lives peaceable, ſober, juſt, and of an humble mind; there is more hope of ſalvation in that man, he is not ſo far from the Kingdom of God, as thoſe that ſin againſt nature; evil and wicked men have ſome principles of knowledge; ye are evil, and yet ye know ſome good things.</p>
            <p>The third truth is, <hi>Ye that are evil,</hi> among the decayes, ruines, and rubbiſh
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:152582:70"/>of nature, yet this truth is preſerved, ye are tender affected Parents, and ſeek the good of your Children; God hath placed this forcible inſtinct, as the bowels of moſt unnatural men is natural love to their Children. In the firſt original, God did create us all one fleſh, and one blood; men were not created apart, as Angels, one independant from another, but all one blood, one root, and the ſap of all this is natural affection; it's this that glues and holds all the world together, it keeps the world in being, without which all would fall aſunder; this tender and kindly affection of parents to Children, it's the Conveyance of all nurture: Thus <hi>Wiſdom</hi> in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> takes upon it the place of a Father, <hi>O my ſon keep the inſtructions of thy father, and what my ſon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>How forcible are theſe perſwaſions to piety and vertue!</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this is a ſpur to labour and induſtry; what's that that keeps the world in action, not all for the belly, but keep ſomething for the Babes; it's that that quickens induſtry, this is the plummet that turns the great Wheel of all the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152582:71"/>world, that makes perpetual motion of labour, to leave ſomething behind for Children.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the ſweetneſs, as that it takes off the harſhneſs of all the toyl and care incident to parents, the care in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth, the care in bringing up; they account it no labour, or a labour much ſweetned by this tender affection. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, that the labour of loving and tender parents to their Children, is either no labour, or ſweet labour.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this tender affection, is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation to piety. <hi>Salvin</hi> urgeth it, Doſt thou love thy Children? be religious and pious; thoſe that are pious claim a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to their Children, and the want of this affection is a ſign of a reprobate mind: Want of this natural affection, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. alſo <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. you may ſee what it is, if na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural affection be wanting, it ſignifies ſome great miſchief. And ſo much for the firſt.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the ſecond, and that's the uſe and improvement that Chriſt makes of it, he cloaths himſelf with this affection, this ſimilitude of a loving Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152582:71"/>to Children; he uſeth this lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, of love to us, conveyes theſe thoughts in the ſweeteſt expreſſions, that we may feel the ſweetneſs of the love of God in the ſweeteſt expreſſions. Take it in three manifeſtations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as to himſelf, the moſt careful reſemblance, compares himſelf to a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; <hi>he that watcheth over Iſrael, neither ſleepeth nor ſlumbereth:</hi> Wouldeſt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Care to feed and provide for thee? he compares himſelf to a Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd that feeds his Sheep: Wouldeſt thou conceive his Tenderneſs? he preſents himſelf as a Hen that gathers her chickens under her wings, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. And as a Hen bears up her wings, <hi>&amp;c. Deut.</hi> 32. or as the Eagle. St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, all of theſe are ſweet reſemblances of his tender Care.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as he takes to himſelf the ſweeteſt reſemblances, ſo the moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving relations, a friend is a ſweet relation, a brother a ſweet relation; <hi>Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, and he was accounted a friend of God; a father is a tender relation, <hi>I will be thy Father;</hi> a husband is a ſweet relation,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152582:72"/>
               <hi>I have married thee to my ſelf:</hi> And becauſe all theſe relations fall ſhort, he joyns all together, <hi>he that doth the will of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is my Father, my Mother, my Brother, &amp;c.</hi> and in the Canticles, <hi>Open unto me, my love, my dove, my undefiled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, he cloaths himſelf with the tender affection of love, as in St. <hi>John;</hi> Pity, that is a tender and melting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, <hi>the Lord is exceeding pitiful,</hi> as in S. <hi>James;</hi> he hath a fellow-feeling of our ſorrows, as in the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> he aſſumes, that he is void of paſſion; nay, he hath bowels of Compaſſion, there's the rowling and turning, and yearning of his bowels. So we have ſeen the firſt main particular of the text, <hi>Ye that are evil and ſinfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion drawn from this Argument; <hi>Your heavenly father knows how to give the holy ſpirit to them that ask him:</hi> Fathers upon earth provide gifts and portions for their Children, but here's the gift of the holy ſpirit. Here are three particulars Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable:</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Donor, <hi>your heavenly Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:152582:72"/>
            <p>Secondly, the gift, <hi>the holy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the qualification of thoſe that receive it, <hi>they muſt ask.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, your heavenly father he is the Donor, look upon it as a hint of incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, <hi>heavenly father;</hi> here's but three words in all.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a father, it's a word of much kindneſs and affection, it argues his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs and propenſity to help us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>heavenly father,</hi> it argues his allſufficiency, God father of heaven, Lord of heaven and earth, he's abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly able to ſupply our neceſſity.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>your heavenly father,</hi> its a word of ingagement; Ye may believe your father; this word gives us our right and portion, that in humble confidence, we may lay Claim to his goodneſs: here's alinck of love, <hi>father, heavenly father, your heavenly father;</hi> theſe three put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether prevents three doubts that faith may object when a Chriſtian is to pray.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the doubt of the poor Leper, <hi>Matt.</hi> 8. <hi>Lord if thou wilt, thou canſt make me clean.</hi> O never queſtion his willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for he is a father, and what will not
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:152582:73"/>a loving father do for his Child.</p>
            <p>The ſecond doubt that faith may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, is the doubt of the poor man for his ſon; <hi>Lord if thou canſt, &amp;c.</hi> He needs not queſtion his power, he is a heavenly father, he hath al-ſufficiency.</p>
            <p>The third doubt is that in <hi>Mark</hi> 4. <hi>Lord, doſt thou not care if we periſh? &amp;c.</hi> never queſtion that, for he is your <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly father,</hi> this it is that makes up a full comfort; without theſe, infidelity would be ready to caſt off all hope, and give over all prayer to God, as thinking God will neither do good nor can; or elſe objects there's no ingagement: Put theſe three together, he's a father, and is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; a heavenly father, and is able; our heavenly father; and therefore ingaged by theſe three, a Child of God hath aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of hope and ſtrong Conſolation.</p>
            <p>Now the gift intended here, is the holy Spirit, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. it's ſaid, <hi>Your heavenly Father gives every good thing;</hi> I, but moſt ſweetly are our prayers Confin'd here to the begging of Gods Spirit; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a Child of God asks, it ſhould be things of neceſſity; ſuperfluity that's not
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:152582:73"/>for Children to ask, nor a wiſe father will give it; the Spirit of God is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, bread is not ſo neceſſary for life, as grace for ſalvation; all neceſſaries for life, and all ſuperfluities are not ſo much, as this abſolute neceſſity of having the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; it's not neceſſary I ſhould live, but it's neceſſary I ſhould be ſanctified and ſaved.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a Child ſhould ask that which is uſeful and profitable, and of all other gifts, the gift of the holy Ghoſt is moſt uſeful, it is a gift of the higheſt nature.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it's the richeſt that God can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow; one dram of grace, one bleſſed ſuggeſtion from the Spirit of truth, one bleſſed motion darted into the heart by the holy Ghoſt, is more worth than all the world: All things in this world may be called good, but makes them not good that have them; St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, Riches are good, if a man have grace to uſe them, ſo he may do good with them, but grace makes good; there's no man can put vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to an evil imployment, grace is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ountain of good; it's the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152582:74"/>the pledge, the aſſurance, it gives all other bleſſings; <hi>Solomon</hi> when he ask'd the ſpirit of wiſdom, God could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him any thing, riches, honours, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if a Child ſhould ask of a father, a ſign of his love, the greateſt manifeſtation of a fathers love; the ſureſt ſign, and richeſt evidence of Gods love, is the gift of the ſpirit, <hi>the love of God when it is ſhed abroad in the heart by the holy Ghoſt;</hi> we feel the taſte of it, rejoyce in the comfort of it, it's a ſeal of Gods love, as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, a dram of Gods grace is a certain token of a determined Election of the aſſurance of glorification; he that asks Gods Spirit loves God, and God love him; ſuch prayers as theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes prevail; <hi>forgive us our ſins, encreaſe our repentance, ſanctifie our ſouls, purge our conſciences, ſubdue our corruptions, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our temptations:</hi> Lord, what prayers ſhould prevail with thee, if ſuch prayers as theſe prevail not; other prayers may hit or miſs, but prayers for Gods Spirit never returns empty.</p>
            <p>Now for the third, the parties, thoſe
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:152582:74"/>that ask, how can we pray for the ſpirit, without the ſpirit, <hi>none can ſay Jeſus is the Lord, but by the holy Ghoſt?</hi> it was the the Pelagian errour to ſay, that our prayers muſt prevent Gods grace; the Spirit of God is not the fruit of our prayers, but our prayers the fruit of Gods Spirit; our deſires are wrought by Gods Spirit, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers our deſires; in this caſe, how ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, indeed his firſt grace, his preventing grace fore-runs all our prayers; <hi>I am found of them that ſought me not:</hi> but his Concomitant grace, that may be the fruit of our prayers, yet all ſupplies of grace are of Gods Spirit; St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, it's the ſureſt ſign of grace, if we deſire grace; prayer it's the breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods Spirit, and there muſt firſt be a drawing in of Gods grace, before there can be aſcending out: <hi>Matth.</hi> 44. there the grace of Gods Spirit; the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven is compared to a treaſure found in the field not look'd for, there's preventing grace, the touch of the ſpirit that works upon the heart in the firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, <hi>verſ.</hi> 45. The Kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is likened unto a Merchant, that ſought
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:152582:75"/>pearls, and found them; here's firſt the grace of prevention, a treaſure found in a field, not thought on, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, faith is given, firſt, as the prime grace, then the prayer of faith, that is the breath; it's prayer that obtaines ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of grace, the matter of our prayer muſt be for the ſupplies of grace, prayer encreaſeth new ſupplies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, prayer may obtain the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling up of our adoption, the kiſs of peace and love, that ſeals up aſſurance of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for ſins.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, beſides the firſt ſtock of grace, look for aſſiſting grace; we can not make good uſe of grace, without the help of grace.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, prayer will obtain the ſpirit of ſtrength and fortitude, to encounter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt temptation; ask thy father this, and he will grant it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, prayer obtains the ſpirit of perſeverance, without the which all holy motions and inſpirations are like a wind, that paſſeth away, and cometh not again.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the Illation drawn from the argument, <hi>how much more;</hi> 'tis a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:152582:75"/>with advantage; indeed it had been well, if the Argument had gon, and the Concluſion drawn with ſome abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, one ſpark of mercy to ſo unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Children; the place of a ſervant, nay, the bread of a ſervant, had been too good for ſo unworthy Children.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if the argument had held but ſo much, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 100. <hi>Like as a father pitieth his own children; or like pity, the Lord teacheth to thoſe that fear him, David</hi> takes comfort in this, but this Scripture offers more grace, how much more? why here's full <hi>meaſure, ſhaken, preſſed down, it runs over.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third expreſſion in this proportion is; if earthly Parents have ſuch provident Care for their Childrens welfare, how much more in God, though earthly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents be never ſo wiſe and provident for their Children, yet they may be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or wiſh things unfit, and to the hurt of their Children, as old <hi>Iſaac</hi> was miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in his bleſſing, the mother of <hi>Zebedees</hi> Children asked ſhe knew not what, but the all-wiſe God hears all our deſires, and orders all things graciouſly for our welfare.</p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:152582:76"/>
            <p>Secondly, Ye men that boaſt of your power, if ye are parents, and have any portion to beſtow upon your Children, how much more God your heavenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; all that earthly fathers enjoy is but borrowed, the oyl in the Cruze may fail, the oyl in the barrell may be ſpent, all ye have is but borrowed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, if ye that are parents have tenderneſs of affection towards your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, how much more your heavenly father? God is full of bounty and mercy, ye are evil and evil natured, <hi>God gives liberally and upbraids not,</hi> to compare with him the goodneſs of men, is not ſo much as one duſt of ſand, to the glory of the whole earth, like a ſpark to the whole element of fire.</p>
            <p>Parents, what do they give to their Children, trifles; God gives the beſt things, his Spirit, his own fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God fils the world with his goodneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, men are but Stepfathers of the fleſh in reſpect of God, he's father both of ſoul and body; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23. <hi>he chargeth, &amp;c.</hi> wordly fathers, <hi>thou haſt taken, &amp;c.</hi> God is our being, and the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:152582:76"/>preſerver of our being. <hi>Abraham knows us not, Jacob hath forgotten us:</hi> And Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Call no man father upon earth,</hi> as to compare with God.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, as the neareſt father, ſo the deareſt affection; the affection of the father or mother are cold and dead, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the ardent affection of God towards us; Parents they firſt beget Children, and then love them: God loves firſt, and then begets us to himſelf; a flowing of nature is parents love, but an eternal love is Gods love; we had a being in him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we had any in our ſelves, <hi>he that planteth the ear, ſhall not be hear?</hi> and he that planteth the tenderneſs of Parents to Children, ſhall not he have Compaſſion? nay, how full muſt he needs be of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion?</p>
            <p>To ſhut up all the height and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of affection in God, muſt require reciprocation on our parts; and it's ſet on a three fold proportion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if ye that are Children caſt care upon your Parents, <hi>Be not careful what ye eat, or drink, or what ye put on, for your heavenly Father careth for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:152582:77"/>
            <p>The proportion of obedience is the ſecond; If reverence be due to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of the fleſh, how much more to the parents of the ſpirit? how much more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and obedience to your heavenly Father?</p>
            <p>The third is the proportion of love; If ye give love to earthly fathers, how much more to your heavenly Father? So you ſee the ſum of the Text is; <hi>Ye that are evil, can give good gifts to your Children; how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the holy Spirit to them that ask him?</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:152582:77"/>
            <p>LEſt Obliquie or Malice ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſe the Candor and Integrity of theſe four Sermons, I was deſired by the Seller of them, to read and cenſure them. Having ſeriouſly peruſed them, I find the true Pourtraicture of the late deceas'd (yet never to be forgotten) moſt reverend Biſhop <hi>Brownrigge.</hi> My cenſure can extend no farther than the Printers Errors; The principal one whereof I find to be in the firſt Sermon, in the firſt pages being a tranſpoſition of the Title: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in ſtead of, <hi>Is the Safety of a Nation True Repentance,</hi> read <hi>True Repentance is the Safety of a Nation.</hi> In ſhort, let me adviſe your charitable minds not to ſtudie how to carp at literal faults, but ſtudy the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and you will ſoon be a ſharer with me in the pleaſure and profit of reading them. This I thought fit to write, as to antidote it againſt the tongues of malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious and envious perſons.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>R. H.</hi> M. A.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152582:78"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152582:78"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152582:79"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152582:79"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
